You're listening to: Apache Kafka Deep Dive: Event Streaming at Scale.
Comprehensive guide to Apache Kafka covering architecture, producers, consumers, Kafka Streams, and production best practices for building event-driven systems.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
Apache Kafka has become the backbone of modern event-driven architectures, processing trillions of messages daily at companies like LinkedIn, Netflix, and Uber.
Unlike traditional message queues, Kafka is designed as a distributed commit log that provides durability, scalability, and real-time data streaming capabilities.
In this guide, we'll explore: Kafka architecture and core concepts.
Producer and consumer patterns.
Kafka Streams for stream processing.
Production deployment and monitoring.
Common patterns and best practices.
Moving on to Kafka Architecture.
Core Concepts.
Next up: Producer Patterns.
Basic Producer (Python).
Producer (Go).
Let's explore Consumer Patterns.
Consumer Group (Python).
Batch Consumer with Error Handling.
Now let's look at Kafka Streams.
Now, let's talk about Schema Registry and Avro.
Moving on to Exactly-Once Semantics.
Next up: Production Configuration.
Let's explore Monitoring with Prometheus.
Now let's look at Kafka vs Alternatives.
Now, let's talk about Best Practices.
Partitioning Strategy: Choose keys that distribute load evenly.
Replication: Use replication factor of 3 for production.
Monitoring: Track consumer lag, throughput, and broker health.
Schema Evolution: Use Avro/Protobuf with Schema Registry.
Idempotency: Enable idempotent producers to prevent duplicates.
Error Handling: Implement Dead Letter Queues for failed messages.
Moving on to Conclusion.
Apache Kafka is essential for building scalable event-driven architectures.
Key takeaways:
Use partitions for parallelism and ordering.
Implement exactly-once semantics for critical workflows.
Monitor consumer lag to ensure timely processing.
Design schemas with evolution in mind.
Consider Kafka Streams for real-time processing.
Next up: Related Articles.
Event-Driven Architecture with Apache Kafka - Design patterns.
Microservices with Go and FastAPI - Build Kafka-powered services.
System Design Interview Guide - Design scalable systems.
Docker & Kubernetes Deployment Guide - Deploy Kafka on K8s.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.