You're listening to: AR/VR Development Getting Started: Complete Beginner's Guide 2026.
Learn AR/VR development from scratch - WebXR, Unity AR Foundation, Apple Vision Pro, Meta Quest 3, Samsung Galaxy XR.
Beginner-friendly guide for Indian developers with code examples.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about The XR Revolution: Why 2026 Is the Year to Start.
You've seen the headlines.
Apple released Vision Pro.
Meta keeps pushing Quest headsets.
Samsung announced Galaxy XR.
Everyone's talking about the "spatial computing" future.
But here's what most people miss: You don't need expensive hardware to start building XR experiences today.
This guide will take you from zero to building your first AR/VR application.
Whether you have a smartphone or a high-end headset, you'll be creating immersive experiences by the end of this article.
Moving on to What Is AR/VR/MR/XR?
(Simple Explanations).
Before we dive into code, let's understand what these acronyms actually mean.
Augmented Reality (AR).
Digital content overlaid on the real world.
Think Pokémon GO, Instagram filters, or IKEA's furniture placement app.
You still see the real world - just with digital elements added on top.
Virtual Reality (VR).
Completely digital environment that replaces the real world.
Put on a VR headset, and you're transported somewhere else entirely.
You see only the virtual world - full immersion.
Mixed Reality (MR).
Digital objects that interact with the real world.
A virtual ball bouncing off your real table.
A digital character sitting on your actual couch.
Real and digital worlds interact - most advanced form.
Extended Reality (XR).
The umbrella term covering AR, VR, and MR. When people say "XR development," they mean building for any or all of these platforms.
Next up: Why Learn XR Development in 2026?.
The numbers tell the story:
What's Changed in 2025-2026?.
Apple Vision Pro brought mainstream attention to spatial computing.
Meta Quest 3 made MR accessible at $499.
WebXR matured - build XR with just JavaScript.
Samsung Galaxy XR (October 2025) brought Android XR to market.
Unity and Unreal simplified cross-platform development.
Let's explore Hardware Landscape 2026: What Should You Buy?.
Here's an honest comparison of current XR hardware:
My Recommendation for Indian Developers.
Start with Meta Quest 3 or Quest 3S.
Here's why:
Best price-to-capability ratio.
Large developer community.
Mixed reality passthrough for AR testing.
WebXR support built-in.
Huge app store for reference.
Available in India through official channels.
You can also start with just your smartphone using WebXR or ARCore/ARKit!
Now let's look at Three Development Paths: Choose Your Journey.
There are three main approaches to XR development:
Decision Flowchart.
Now, let's talk about Path 1: WebXR Development (The Easiest Start).
WebXR is the most accessible way to start XR development.
You use JavaScript, HTML, and Three.js to create VR/AR experiences that run directly in the browser.
What Is WebXR?.
Setting Up Your WebXR Development Environment.
Step 1: Install Node.js
Step 2: Create Project Structure
Step 3: Create Files
Your First VR Scene (Three.js + WebXR).
Let's build a VR environment step by step.
index.html:
Run your project:
Open your browser to the local server address.
If you have a VR headset connected, click "Enter VR"!
A-Frame: Even Easier XR Development.
A-Frame is a web framework that makes XR development as simple as writing HTML.
Complete A-Frame Example:
That's it!
Save this as an HTML file, open it in a browser, and you have a VR scene.
No build tools required.
AR with A-Frame (Marker-based).
Print a HIRO marker (search "HIRO marker AR.js"), point your phone camera at it, and watch the 3D cube appear!
Testing Without Hardware: Meta Immersive Web Emulator.
You don't need a VR headset to test WebXR.
Install the Meta Immersive Web Emulator Chrome extension:
Moving on to Path 2: Unity AR Foundation (Cross-Platform Power).
Unity is the industry standard for XR development.
AR Foundation provides a unified API for ARCore (Android), ARKit (iOS), and other platforms.
Setting Up Unity for XR Development.
Understanding AR Foundation Architecture.
Essential AR Foundation Components.
Building Your First AR App: Object Placer.
Let's create an AR app that places 3D objects on detected surfaces.
Step 1: Scene Setup
Step 2: Create the Placement Script
Step 3: Plane Visualization Script
Face Tracking (iOS ARKit).
Next up: Path 3: Platform-Specific Development.
For maximum performance and access to cutting-edge features, native development is the way.
Meta Quest Development (Unity + Meta XR SDK).
Quest Hand Tracking Example:
Apple Vision Pro Development (visionOS).
Apple Vision Pro uses SwiftUI and RealityKit for native development.
Samsung Galaxy XR / Android XR.
Samsung Galaxy XR runs Android XR, Google's new operating system for headsets.
Let's explore Indian XR Ecosystem.
Indian XR Startups to Watch.
Job Market and Salaries.
Learning Resources.
Free Resources:
Meta Quest Developer Hub - Official tutorials and documentation.
Unity Learn - Free XR development courses.
A-Frame School - Interactive WebXR tutorials.
Google ARCore Codelabs - Step-by-step AR tutorials.
Paid Courses:
Udemy: Complete XR Development - ₹449-3,999.
Coursera: XR Specialization - ₹3,000/month.
Unity Certified Developer - $150 exam.
Indian XR Communities.
XR Association India - Industry body.
VRARA India - Virtual Reality AR Association.
XR Developers India (Discord) - 5,000+ members.
Bangalore XR Meetup - Monthly events.
Mumbai VR - Active community.
Now let's look at Project: AR Business Card.
Let's build a complete project - an AR business card that displays your portfolio when someone scans it.
Concept.
Implementation (A-Frame + AR.js).
Now, let's talk about VR Portfolio Gallery (Three.js).
For a more immersive portfolio experience:
Moving on to Deployment Guide.
Deploying WebXR to the Web.
Deploying to Meta Quest (Unity).
Deploying to iOS (Unity AR Foundation).
Next up: 2026-2027 XR Outlook.
Let's explore Quick Reference: XR Development Commands.
Now let's look at Common Beginner Mistakes (And How to Avoid Them).
Now, let's talk about Conclusion: Your XR Journey Starts Now.
You've learned:
What XR is - AR, VR, MR, and the umbrella term XR.
Hardware landscape - Quest 3, Vision Pro, Galaxy XR options.
Three development paths - WebXR, Unity, and Native.
WebXR basics - Three.js and A-Frame for browser-based XR.
Unity AR Foundation - Cross-platform mobile AR development.
Platform-specific features - Quest, Vision Pro, Android XR.
Indian ecosystem - Jobs, salaries, communities.
Complete projects - AR business card, VR portfolio.
Your next steps:
Today: Install development tools (Node.js for WebXR or Unity).
This week: Complete your first VR scene (use the Three.js code above).
This month: Build the AR business card project.
Next month: Deploy your first app to Quest or web.
The XR industry is growing fast, and there's never been a better time to start.
The barrier to entry is low (you can start with just a browser), but the ceiling is incredibly high.
Welcome to the future of computing.
Moving on to Resources.
Official Documentation.
WebXR Device API (MDN).
Three.js Documentation.
A-Frame Documentation.
Unity AR Foundation.
Meta Quest Developer.
Apple visionOS.
Learning Platforms.
Unity Learn - XR.
Meta Quest Developer Hub.
Immersive Web Working Group.
Communities.
WebXR Discord.
r/WebXR.
r/OculusQuest.
XR Developers India.
This guide is part of my series on emerging technologies for Indian developers.
Follow for more in-depth technical guides.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.