You're listening to: Authentication & Authorization: Complete Guide to JWT, OAuth 2.0, and Security.
Master authentication and authorization in web applications.
Learn JWT tokens, OAuth 2.0 flows, session management, RBAC, and security best practices with Python and Node.js implementations.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
Authentication and authorization are the gatekeepers of every secure application.
At Dr. Dangs Lab, we handle sensitive healthcare data requiring robust security.
This guide covers everything from basic concepts to production-ready implementations.
Moving on to Authentication vs Authorization.
Next up: JWT (JSON Web Tokens).
JWT Structure.
JWT Implementation (Python/FastAPI).
Let's explore OAuth 2.0.
OAuth 2.0 Flows.
OAuth 2.
0 Implementation (Google Login).
Now let's look at Role-Based Access Control (RBAC).
Now, let's talk about Security Best Practices.
1. Secure Token Storage (Frontend).
2. Password Security.
3. Rate Limiting for Auth Endpoints.
Moving on to Key Takeaways.
Use JWT for stateless auth - Scalable and works with microservices.
Implement refresh tokens - Short-lived access tokens + long-lived refresh tokens.
Hash passwords properly - Use bcrypt or argon2.
Use HTTPS everywhere - Never transmit tokens over HTTP.
Implement RBAC - Fine-grained permission control.
Rate limit auth endpoints - Prevent brute force attacks.
Secure token storage - httpOnly cookies or in-memory for SPAs.
Next up: Conclusion.
Authentication and authorization are critical for application security.
Use JWT for scalable stateless authentication, implement OAuth for social logins, and always follow security best practices.
The key is defense in depth—multiple layers of security working together.
Building secure applications?
Connect on LinkedIn to discuss authentication strategies.
Let's explore Related Articles.
REST API Design Best Practices - Build secure, well-designed APIs.
React Server Components Security Vulnerabilities - Frontend security concerns.
HIPAA Compliance for Healthcare SaaS - Healthcare security standards.
TypeScript Best Practices - Type-safe authentication code.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.