You're listening to: AWS Services for Backend Developers: Complete Infrastructure Guide.
Master essential AWS services for backend development including EC2, Lambda, S3, RDS, DynamoDB, SQS, SNS, API Gateway, and CloudFormation.
Learn cloud architecture patterns and best practices.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
Amazon Web Services (AWS) offers 200+ services, but backend developers typically use a core set of 15-20 services regularly.
This guide covers the essential AWS services every backend developer should master, with practical examples and architecture patterns.
Moving on to Compute Services.
EC2 (Elastic Compute Cloud).
Virtual servers for running applications.
Lambda (Serverless Functions).
Run code without managing servers.
ECS/Fargate (Container Orchestration).
Run Docker containers at scale.
Next up: Storage Services.
S3 (Simple Storage Service).
Object storage for files, backups, static assets.
Let's explore Database Services.
RDS (Relational Database Service).
Managed PostgreSQL, MySQL, and more.
DynamoDB (NoSQL Database).
Serverless, scalable NoSQL database.
Now let's look at Messaging Services.
SQS (Simple Queue Service).
Message queuing for async processing.
SNS (Simple Notification Service).
Pub/Sub messaging for notifications.
Now, let's talk about API Gateway.
Create REST and WebSocket APIs.
Moving on to Infrastructure as Code.
CloudFormation/CDK.
Next up: Best Practices.
1. Security.
2. Cost Optimization.
3. Monitoring.
Let's explore Conclusion.
Mastering these AWS services enables you to build scalable, reliable backend systems.
Start with the basics (EC2, S3, RDS), then progress to serverless (Lambda, DynamoDB) and event-driven architectures (SQS, SNS).
Building on AWS?
Connect on LinkedIn to discuss cloud architecture and best practices.
Now let's look at Related Articles.
Docker & Kubernetes Deployment Guide - Container orchestration on AWS.
System Design Interview Guide - Design cloud-native systems.
PostgreSQL Performance Optimization - Optimize RDS databases.
Redis Caching Strategies Complete Guide - ElastiCache patterns.
GitHub Actions CI/CD Complete Guide - Deploy to AWS with CI/CD.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.