You're listening to: Building Scalable Microservices with Go and FastAPI.
How I learned to combine Go and Python microservices the hard way - after our monolith crashed during peak hours at Dr. Dangs Lab. Real patterns from processing millions of healthcare transactions.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about The Day Our Monolith Died.
It was 9:47 AM on a Monday.
Our lab management system at Dr. Dangs Lab had just crashed.
200+ patients were waiting for their reports, 80 doctors couldn't access test results, and my phone wouldn't stop buzzing.
The culprit?
Our Python monolith was trying to process 500 lab reports simultaneously while handling API requests.
CPU hit 100%, memory exhausted, and the whole thing came down.
That day taught me why microservices exist - not as a trendy architecture choice, but as a survival mechanism.
Moving on to Why I Ended Up Using Both Go and FastAPI.
After the crash, I spent two weeks analyzing our workloads.
Here's what I found:
CPU-bound work (report processing, PDF generation): Python was spending 80% of time waiting for GIL locks.
Processing 100 reports took 45 seconds.
Memory usage spiked unpredictably.
I/O-bound work (API requests, database queries): Most requests were waiting on database/network.
Python's async was actually fine here.
Developer velocity mattered more than raw speed.
The answer became obvious: Go for the heavy lifting, Python for everything else.
The Performance Difference Was Shocking.
I rewrote our report processor in Go as an experiment:
Results: 100 reports: 45 seconds → 3 seconds.
Memory: 2GB spikes → stable 200MB. CPU: 100% single core → distributed across 8 cores.
I was sold.
But I wasn't about to rewrite our entire API layer in Go - that would take months and our team knew Python inside out.
Next up: Our Hybrid Architecture.
Here's what we actually built:
FastAPI Handles the API Layer.
I kept all patient-facing APIs in FastAPI.
Why?
Because I could ship features in hours, not days:
Go Handles the Heavy Processing.
When a batch of lab results comes in, FastAPI hands it off to our Go service:
Let's explore The Communication Problem (And How I Almost Got It Wrong).
My first attempt at connecting the services was... embarrassing.
What Actually Works: Batch + Async.
For Real-Time Stuff: gRPC.
When we needed real-time status updates (doctors waiting for urgent results), HTTP polling was too slow.
gRPC streaming solved it:
The streaming version meant doctors saw results appearing in real-time instead of waiting for the whole batch.
For Decoupled Work: Kafka.
Some things don't need immediate responses.
When a report is finalized, multiple systems need to know:
Now let's look at The Distributed Transaction Nightmare.
Here's a scenario that kept me up at night:
Patient pays for a test.
Sample is collected.
Payment fails (card declined after initial auth).
Sample is already in the lab.
???.
In a monolith, you'd wrap it in a database transaction.
With microservices, that's not possible.
The Saga Pattern Saved Us.
Now, let's talk about Deployment: What Actually Runs in Production.
After getting burned by "it works on my machine" too many times:
Moving on to Monitoring: Because You Can't Fix What You Can't See.
After our third "silent failure" incident, I made observability non-negotiable:
Next up: What I'd Do Differently.
Looking back after 2 years of running this in production:
Start with a monolith - We extracted services too early.
Should have waited for clear pain points..
Shared database was fine initially - The "each service owns its data" rule caused more problems than it solved for our team size..
gRPC from day one - HTTP was easier to start but we eventually rewrote all internal communication to gRPC anyway..
Invest in local dev environment - Running 5 services locally was painful until we set up docker-compose properly..
Contract testing - Integration tests were flaky.
Consumer-driven contract tests (Pact) would have saved hours of debugging..
Let's explore The Results.
After 18 months:
Metric, Monolith, Microservices.
Report processing, 45s/batch, 3s/batch.
API latency p99, 2.1s, 180ms.
Deployment frequency, Weekly, Daily.
Incidents/month, 4-5, 0-1.
Time to add new feature, 2-3 days, 4-6 hours.
Was it worth it?
Absolutely.
But I wouldn't recommend it for every project.
We needed it because our scale demanded it.
Now let's look at Wrapping Up.
The combination of Go for performance-critical paths and FastAPI for rapid API development has worked incredibly well for us.
But the real lesson isn't about languages - it's about:
Understanding your actual bottlenecks before optimizing.
Keeping services focused and small.
Investing heavily in observability.
Accepting that distributed systems are inherently complex.
If you're considering microservices, ask yourself: do you actually need them, or is your monolith just poorly structured?
Often, a well-organized monolith is the right answer.
Got questions about this architecture?
I've made plenty of mistakes not covered here - feel free to reach out on LinkedIn or check out more of my work on GitHub.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.