You're listening to: Building Backends for AI Agents: Idempotency, Retries & State (2026).
AI agents retry, run for minutes, and call your APIs in unpredictable loops.
The backend is where agent reliability lives.
A practical guide to idempotency, safe retries, durable state, and observability for agent-facing systems in 2026.
Let's get started.
There's a line going around in 2026 that I think is exactly right: the backend is where agent reliability lives.
All the attention goes to the model and the prompts, but when an AI agent does something wrong — charges twice, corrupts state, loops forever — the failure is almost always in the backend it was calling, not the model.
Agents are just a new, unusually chaotic kind of API client, and most backends were not built for a client that retries aggressively, runs for minutes, and calls your endpoints in loops it decides at runtime.
This is a practical guide to building backends that stay correct when an agent is driving.
It pulls together patterns I've written about individually — idempotency keys, event-driven design, rate limiting — into one mental model for agent-facing systems.
Now, let's talk about Why agents break backends that humans don't.
A human client is predictable: one click, one request, a sensible pause, a retry only when they're frustrated.
An agent is the opposite:
It retries reflexively.
When a tool call times out or returns an error, the agent's loop often just calls it again — sometimes many times, fast..
It runs long.
A single agent task can span minutes of tool calls, far past a normal HTTP timeout..
It calls tools in runtime-decided loops.
You can't predict the sequence or the volume; the agent composes it on the fly..
It acts on stale beliefs.
An agent may decide to "create the order" based on context that's already changed..
Each of these maps to a backend property you must now guarantee: idempotency, durable long-running execution, rate limiting and loop-breaking, and consistent state.
Get those four right and agents become a manageable client.
Skip them and you get the 2026 version of the double-charge bug — except the agent does it ten times in four seconds.
Moving on to 1.
Idempotency is non-negotiable now.
For human-facing APIs, idempotency is good hygiene.
For agent-facing APIs, it is mandatory, because the agent will retry, and you have no control over when.
Every state-changing tool an agent can call must be safe to call repeatedly.
The pattern is the same one I detailed in idempotency keys: the caller supplies a key, you claim it atomically, and you replay the stored result on duplicates.
The practical twist for agents: you often have to generate the key for them.
Many agent frameworks don't supply one.
A robust approach is to derive a deterministic key from (agent_run_id, tool_name, canonical_args_hash) — so the same logical action within a run collapses to one key even if the agent doesn't think to send one.
Next up: 2. Make destructive tools hard to fire by accident.
Idempotency stops duplicate harm.
You also want to limit first-time harm from an agent that misunderstands its task.
Two cheap guards:
Confirmation tokens for irreversible actions.
A "delete customer" tool returns a preview + a token; the action only executes when called again with that token.
This forces a two-step the agent must consciously complete..
Dry-run by default for high-blast-radius tools.
Return what would happen; require an explicit commit: true.
Agents tend to do the safe thing when the safe thing is the default..
These aren't agent-specific inventions — they're the same defensive instincts behind good REST API design — but agents raise the stakes enough that they're worth making mandatory for anything destructive.
Let's explore 3.
Rate limit per agent run, and break loops.
A buggy agent can hammer a tool in a tight loop.
Standard per-user rate limiting helps, but the more useful unit for agents is the agent run.
Track calls per agent_run_id and:
Cap total tool calls per run.
A hard ceiling ("this run may call tools 200 times") turns an infinite loop into a bounded, debuggable failure..
Detect repetition.
If the same (tool, args_hash) is called N times in a run with no state change, that's a loop — return an error that tells the agent to stop, not the same result that keeps it spinning..
The token-bucket and gateway patterns in rate limiting & API gateway patterns apply directly; you're just keying them on the run instead of the user.
Now let's look at 4.
State: agents need durable, inspectable execution.
Because agent tasks are long and multi-step, you cannot hold their progress in a request handler's memory — a deploy, crash, or timeout would lose it.
Agent backends need durable state: the run, its steps, and its tool results persisted so the work can resume and so you can inspect what happened.
This is where event-driven thinking pays off.
Model an agent run as an append-only event log — run_started, tool_called, tool_result, step_completed — exactly the event-driven architecture pattern.
Benefits:
Recoverability.
Rebuild run state by replaying its events after a crash..
Auditability.
When an agent does something surprising, the event log is the trace of why..
Idempotent resume.
Combined with the action keys above, you can re-drive a run without repeating completed side effects..
For long-running execution specifically, don't block the HTTP request for minutes — kick the work to a durable queue and let the agent poll or subscribe.
I cover that pattern in depth in designing async, long-running APIs for AI agents.
Now, let's talk about 5.
Observability: you cannot debug what you cannot see.
Agent failures are weird and intermittent.
Without tracing, "the agent did something bad yesterday" is unfixable.
Instrument every tool call with the agent_run_id as a trace/correlation ID, and emit the same percentile metrics you'd use anywhere — the Prometheus/Grafana/Jaeger stack works unchanged.
The one addition for agents: log the arguments and decision, not just latency, because the interesting failure is usually "why did it call this tool with these args," not "how slow was it."
Moving on to The checklist for an agent-ready backend.
Every state-changing tool is idempotent — caller key or server-derived (run, tool, args) key..
Destructive tools are two-step — confirmation tokens or dry-run-by-default..
Rate limits and loop detection are keyed on the agent run, with a hard call ceiling..
Runs are durable, append-only event logs — recoverable, auditable, resumable..
Long work is async, off the request path (details here)..
Every tool call is traced by run ID, with arguments captured..
Next up: The takeaway.
The agent era doesn't require exotic new backend theory — it requires you to actually apply the reliability patterns we already knew, because the new client punishes every shortcut.
Idempotency, durable state, run-scoped rate limits, and tracing were "nice to have" for human traffic.
For agents they're the difference between a tool an agent can safely use and a footgun it fires on your behalf.
Build the backend as if a fast, slightly confused client is in control of it — because in 2026, one is.
Related reading: Idempotency Keys: How We Stopped Double-Charging Customers.
Designing Async, Long-Running APIs for AI Agents.
MCP vs Direct API Calls: The Token-Efficiency Debate (2026).
Event-Driven Architecture with Kafka.
AI-Native Backend Architecture for 2026.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.