You're listening to: Cryptographic Bill of Materials (CBOM): Step 1 of PQC Migration.
You can't migrate cryptography you can't see.
A practical guide to building a Cryptographic Bill of Materials — what to inventory, how to find hidden crypto, how to score by data lifetime, and how the CBOM becomes your post-quantum migration plan.
Let's get started.
Every serious post-quantum migration plan starts with the same unglamorous step, and almost everyone wants to skip it: find all your cryptography first.
Not the crypto you think you use — the crypto you actually use, including the dependency three levels down that pins an RSA key, the legacy service nobody owns, and the TLS config you've never looked at.
That inventory has a name now: a Cryptographic Bill of Materials (CBOM).
Building one is genuinely the highest-leverage thing you can do in 2026, because every later decision depends on it.
This is the practical how-to.
It's the concrete first move behind the PQC deadlines and the migration guide.
Now, let's talk about Why a CBOM, and why now.
The logic is simple: you cannot protect, prioritize, or replace what you can't see.
NIST, the NCSC, and every enterprise migration framework converge on inventory-first for a reason — the alternative is migrating blind and discovering the RSA you missed during an incident.
A CBOM is to cryptography what an SBOM (Software Bill of Materials) is to dependencies: a structured, maintained record of every cryptographic asset, where it's used, and its risk.
The "harvest now, decrypt later" threat makes it urgent — data being captured today is already on the clock, and you can't triage it without knowing where it lives.
Moving on to What goes in a CBOM.
For each cryptographic usage, capture enough to make a migration decision:
Field, Why it matters.
Asset / location, Service, endpoint, library, or file where crypto is used.
Algorithm & key size, RSA-2048, ECC P-256, AES-256… — what needs replacing vs what's fine.
Purpose, Key exchange, signature, or data-at-rest encryption (determines ML-KEM vs ML-DSA vs nothing).
Data confidentiality lifetime, How long the protected data must stay secret — the priority driver.
Owner, Who can actually change it.
Crypto-agility, Is the algorithm swappable, or hard-coded?.
That fourth row — data lifetime — is the one most inventories forget and the most important.
A session token that's worthless in 15 minutes and a medical record that must stay private for 30 years are completely different risks, even if both use the same algorithm.
Next up: The hard part: finding crypto you forgot you had.
The visible crypto is easy.
The dangerous crypto is hidden.
Hunt in all of these places:
TLS everywhere — public endpoints, internal mTLS between services, database connections, message-broker TLS, VPNs..
Tokens and signatures — JWT signing keys, API request signing, code/firmware signing, document signing..
Data at rest — disk/volume encryption, encrypted database columns, encrypted backups and archives (these have the longest lifetimes — backups from today might be restored in 2040)..
Dependencies — the crypto your libraries use internally.
A package.json or requirements.txt doesn't show you that a transitive dependency pins an algorithm.
This is where automated scanning earns its keep..
Certificates and PKI — your CA hierarchy, cert algorithms, and key sizes..
Secrets managers and HSMs — what algorithms they're configured for..
Practical tactics: scan source for crypto API calls and hard-coded algorithm names, enumerate TLS configs across hosts, pull certificate inventories, and use SBOM/dependency tooling to surface library-level crypto.
The goal of the first pass isn't perfection — it's to stop being blind.
Let's explore Turn the inventory into a priority order.
A raw list isn't a plan.
Sort it.
Rank each asset by roughly:
Urgent: long-lived secrets crossing capturable networks — health, financial, legal, government data; long-retention backups.
These are the harvest-now-decrypt-later targets.
Migrate (in hybrid mode) first..
Important: medium-lifetime data and broadly-exposed signing keys..
Later: ephemeral data whose value evaporates quickly — short sessions, transient caches..
This sorted list is your migration roadmap.
You're not migrating "the company"; you're migrating the top of this list first.
Now let's look at Note crypto-agility while you're in there.
For each asset, record whether the algorithm is swappable or hard-coded.
This does double duty: it tells you the effort to migrate each item, and it surfaces the architectural debt you need to pay down.
Hard-coded crypto is what turns migration into a multi-quarter slog; flagging it now lets you prioritize adding an agility layer where it'll hurt most.
Now, let's talk about Keep it alive.
A CBOM is not a one-time spreadsheet — it's a living artifact, like an SBOM.
New services add crypto; dependencies change algorithms.
Wire inventory updates into your process: a CI check that flags new cryptographic dependencies, a periodic re-scan, and ownership so it doesn't rot.
The teams that will swap algorithms calmly when the 2030 deprecation lands are the ones whose CBOM is current and trusted.
Moving on to The takeaway.
Building a Cryptographic Bill of Materials is the boring, decisive first step of post-quantum migration.
Inventory every cryptographic use, hunt down the hidden ones (dependencies and backups especially), tag each with its data-confidentiality lifetime, and sort by risk.
What falls out is a prioritized migration plan grounded in reality instead of guesswork.
Start it in 2026 — before the deadlines force you to do it under pressure, and before you find the RSA you missed the hard way.
Related reading: Post-Quantum Cryptography Deadlines: 2027, 2030 & 2035.
Migrating to Post-Quantum Cryptography: A Practical Developer Guide (2026).
Hybrid Cryptography: Why Ed25519 + ML-DSA Is the Safe Migration Path.
QuantumShield: Building a Post-Quantum Cryptography Library from Scratch.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.