You're listening to: Database Connection Pooling: The Performance Fix That Saved Our Production.
How I learned about connection pooling after our PostgreSQL database crashed under load.
Practical guide with real configurations from handling millions of healthcare queries.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about The Monday Morning That Changed Everything.
It was 9:15 AM.
Our busiest time - patients arriving for their morning appointments, doctors pulling up test results, lab techs entering data from overnight samples.
Then everything stopped.
PostgreSQL had hit max_connections.
Our app had 3 instances, each opening 50 connections, but PostgreSQL was configured for 100 max.
We were at 150 attempted connections and the database was refusing new ones.
Error logs filled with:
Patients couldn't see their reports.
Doctors couldn't access histories.
Sample tracking went dark.
We scrambled to restart services, but they'd immediately exhaust connections again.
The only fix was killing application instances one by one until we got back under the limit.
That day cost us 47 minutes of downtime and a lot of angry phone calls.
It also taught me everything I now know about connection pooling.
Moving on to Why This Happens (And Why I Didn't See It Coming).
I'd always thought "just add more connections" was the answer.
More connections = more queries = better performance, right?
Completely wrong.
Here's what was happening in our system:
Next up: The Fix: Connection Pooling.
After that incident, I spent a week understanding connection pooling.
The concept is simple:
Instead of each request opening a new connection, requests borrow from a pool and return when done.
The pool maintains a fixed number of actual database connections.
Let's explore What I Actually Implemented.
Application-Level Pooling with asyncpg.
For our FastAPI services, I used asyncpg with a properly configured pool:
The Pool Sizing Formula That Actually Works.
I spent way too long trying different pool sizes.
Here's the formula I settled on:
I tried 50 connections once thinking "more is better."
The database got slower, not faster.
Too many connections means PostgreSQL spends more time scheduling processes than running queries.
FastAPI Integration.
Here's how we wire it up in FastAPI:
Now let's look at PgBouncer: When Application Pooling Isn't Enough.
After a few months, we hit another problem.
We had 5 application instances, each with a pool of 20 connections.
That's 100 connections to PostgreSQL - right at our limit again.
Enter PgBouncer - a connection pooler that sits between your applications and PostgreSQL.
My PgBouncer Configuration.
The pool_mode = transaction setting is crucial.
It means connections are returned to the pool after each transaction completes, not when the client disconnects.
This dramatically improves connection reuse.
Running PgBouncer in Docker.
Now, let's talk about Monitoring: How I Catch Problems Before They Crash Production.
After the Monday incident, I added monitoring for everything pool-related:
Alerts I Have Set Up.
Moving on to Common Mistakes I Made (So You Don't Have To).
Mistake 1: Pool Too Large.
Bigger isn't better.
200 connections to PostgreSQL means 200 processes competing for resources.
Mistake 2: Forgetting to Release Connections.
Mistake 3: Holding Connections During Slow Operations.
The first version holds a connection for 2+ seconds.
The second version holds it for milliseconds.
Next up: The Results.
After implementing proper connection pooling:
Metric, Before, After.
Max PostgreSQL connections, 100 → always hitting limit, 30 → plenty of headroom.
Connection errors, 50-100/day, 0.
Query latency p99, 800ms, 45ms.
App instances supported, 2, 10+.
The 47-minute outage never happened again.
And when traffic spikes, instead of crashing, we just queue requests briefly while waiting for connections.
Let's explore My Checklist for New Projects.
Connection pooling isn't glamorous, but it's the difference between a system that scales and one that falls over under load.
I learned this the hard way so you don't have to.
The patterns here have handled millions of queries per day in production.
They'll probably handle yours too.
Questions about database performance?
I've debugged more connection issues than I'd like to admit.
Reach out on LinkedIn.
Now let's look at Related Articles.
PostgreSQL Performance Optimization - Query tuning and indexes.
Database Sharding Guide - Horizontal scaling.
Building Scalable Microservices - Service architecture.
Redis Caching Strategies - Reducing database load.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.