You're listening to: Docker and Kubernetes: Complete Deployment Guide for Production.
Master containerization with Docker and orchestration with Kubernetes.
Learn to build, deploy, and scale applications with practical examples, best practices, and production-ready configurations.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
Containerization has revolutionized how we build, ship, and run applications.
At Dr. Dangs Lab, we've containerized over 50 microservices and manage them across multiple Kubernetes clusters.
In this guide, I'll share practical knowledge from deploying healthcare applications at scale.
Moving on to Why Docker + Kubernetes?.
The Problem They Solve.
Before Containers: "It works on my machine" syndrome.
Complex dependency management.
Inconsistent environments.
Slow, error-prone deployments.
With Docker + Kubernetes: Consistent environments everywhere.
Isolated, reproducible builds.
Automated scaling and healing.
Zero-downtime deployments.
Next up: Docker Fundamentals.
Writing Production-Ready Dockerfiles.
Docker Compose for Development.
Docker Best Practices.
Let's explore Kubernetes Fundamentals.
Core Concepts.
Deployment Configuration.
Service and Ingress.
ConfigMaps and Secrets.
Now let's look at Horizontal Pod Autoscaling.
Now, let's talk about CI/CD Pipeline Integration.
Moving on to Monitoring and Observability.
Prometheus Metrics.
Kubernetes Monitoring Stack.
Next up: Key Takeaways.
Use multi-stage builds to minimize image size.
Never run as root in containers.
Set resource limits to prevent noisy neighbors.
Implement proper health checks for reliable orchestration.
Use namespaces for environment isolation.
Enable HPA for automatic scaling.
Store secrets securely with Kubernetes Secrets or external vaults.
Implement proper logging and monitoring from day one.
Let's explore Conclusion.
Docker and Kubernetes form the backbone of modern cloud-native applications.
While the learning curve is steep, the benefits—consistency, scalability, and reliability—make it worthwhile.
Start with Docker locally, then graduate to Kubernetes as your needs grow.
Building containerized applications?
Connect on LinkedIn to discuss deployment strategies.
Now let's look at Related Articles.
AWS Services for Backend Developers - Deploy containers on AWS ECS/EKS.
GitHub Actions CI/CD Complete Guide - Automate your Docker builds.
Nginx Reverse Proxy & Load Balancing - Configure ingress for containers.
System Design Interview Guide - Design scalable containerized systems.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.