You're listening to: Docker Tutorial for Beginners 2026: Complete Guide with Examples.
Learn Docker from scratch in 2026.
Step-by-step tutorial covering containers, images, Dockerfile, Docker Compose, and deployment.
Perfect for Indian developers starting with containerization.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Why Learn Docker in 2026?.
Docker has become an essential skill for developers.
Whether you're deploying to AWS, working with Kubernetes, or just want consistent development environments, Docker is the foundation.
Moving on to What is Docker?.
Docker is a platform that packages your application and all its dependencies into a container - a lightweight, standalone unit that runs consistently anywhere.
Next up: Docker Concepts.
Containers vs Virtual Machines.
Key Terms.
Let's explore Installing Docker.
On Ubuntu/Debian.
On macOS.
On Windows.
Now let's look at Your First Docker Commands.
Running Containers.
Managing Containers.
Managing Images.
Now, let's talk about Writing Your First Dockerfile.
Python Application.
Build and Run.
Node.js Application.
Multi-Stage Build (Optimized).
Moving on to Dockerfile Best Practices.
Next up: Docker Compose.
Docker Compose manages multi-container applications.
Basic docker-compose.yml.
Docker Compose Commands.
Full-Stack Example.
Let's explore Docker Networking.
Now let's look at Docker Volumes.
Now, let's talk about Deploying Docker to Production.
Push to Docker Hub.
Deploy to AWS EC2.
Deploy with Docker Compose.
Moving on to Common Docker Commands Cheat Sheet.
Next up: Troubleshooting.
Let's explore Next Steps.
Now let's look at Conclusion.
Docker is a foundational skill for modern development.
Start with simple containers, progress to Docker Compose, and eventually explore Kubernetes for production orchestration.
Practice Project: Dockerize your existing project today!
Learning Docker?
Connect with me on LinkedIn for more DevOps tips.
Now, let's talk about Related Articles.
Backend Developer Roadmap 2026.
System Design Interview Questions.
FastAPI vs Django.
Database Connection Pooling.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.