You're listening to: Event-Driven Architecture with Apache Kafka: A Practical Guide.
Learn how to design and implement event-driven systems using Apache Kafka.
Covers event schemas, consumer patterns, exactly-once semantics, and real-world patterns from healthcare data pipelines.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
At Dr. Dangs Lab, we process over 100,000 lab reports daily, each triggering a cascade of events—notifications to patients, updates to medical records, billing operations, and analytics pipelines.
Traditional request-response architectures couldn't handle this scale efficiently.
Enter Apache Kafka and event-driven architecture.
Moving on to Why Event-Driven?.
Traditional vs Event-Driven.
Traditional (Request-Response
Event-Driven:
Benefits.
Loose coupling: Services don't need to know about each other.
Scalability: Add consumers without modifying producers.
Resilience: Services can fail independently.
Replay ability: Events can be replayed for debugging or recovery.
Next up: Setting Up Kafka.
Docker Compose Configuration.
Creating Topics.
Let's explore Event Schema Design.
Using Avro for Schema Evolution.
Now let's look at Producer Implementation.
Async Producer with Retries.
Now, let's talk about Consumer Implementation.
Resilient Consumer with Error Handling.
Moving on to Advanced Patterns.
Saga Pattern for Distributed Transactions.
Consumer Groups for Scaling.
Next up: Monitoring and Observability.
Key Metrics to Track.
Let's explore Key Takeaways.
Design events, not APIs: Think about what happened, not what to do.
Use schemas: Avro or Protobuf for type safety and evolution.
Partition wisely: Choose partition keys that ensure ordering where needed.
Handle failures: Implement DLQs and retry mechanisms.
Monitor everything: Consumer lag is your early warning system.
Now let's look at Conclusion.
Event-driven architecture with Kafka has transformed how we handle data at scale.
The decoupling it provides allows us to add new features without touching existing services, and the replay capability has saved us countless times during incident recovery.
Building event-driven systems?
Let's connect on LinkedIn to discuss patterns and best practices.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.