You're listening to: FOMOA AI: The Complete Guide to India's Free AI Search Engine (2026).
Everything about FOMOA AI — India's free AI search engine.
Native Hindi/Hinglish support, 150+ Indian sources, a 4-signal credibility ranking system, government scheme search, and how it was trained on 86,000 India-centric samples.
Let's get started.
Generic AI models were not built for India.
Ask one "मेरी सैलरी 12 लाख है, टैक्स कितना लगेगा?" and it stumbles on the number format before it even gets to the tax slabs.
Ask it which government scheme a small farmer qualifies for and it confidently invents one.
That gap is exactly why I got interested in FOMOA — an India-first AI search engine that is free to use, understands Hindi and Hinglish natively, and ranks answers by how trustworthy the source actually is.
This is the complete guide: what FOMOA is, why an India-first engine matters, the features that make it different, how it ranks results, and how it was actually trained.
If you only read one FOMOA article, read this one.
Now, let's talk about What is FOMOA AI?.
FOMOA is a free AI search engine optimised for Indian users and Indian context.
Instead of bolting an "India mode" onto a global model, it was built from the ground up around three things global tools get wrong:
Language — Indians search in Hindi, English, and a constant code-mix of both ("Hinglish").
FOMOA detects the language automatically and answers in kind..
Sources — it draws on 150+ authoritative Indian sources (government portals, regulators, major Indian publications) instead of treating a random blog as equal to an official notification..
Format — it understands the Indian number system (lakhs, crores), Indian dates, and the structure of Indian government schemes..
You can use it as a normal web search assistant, or — if you are a developer — through an OpenAI-compatible API.
I cover the developer side in depth in the companion guide, FOMOA for Developers.
Moving on to Why an India-First Engine Matters.
Here is where global AI models consistently fail Indian users:
1. The Indian number system.
"12 lakh" is 1,200,000.
"2.5 crore" is 25,000,000.
Global models frequently misread these, and a single misread digit destroys a tax, loan, or salary answer.
FOMOA treats lakh/crore as first-class units.
2. Source credibility blindness.
Most AI search treats Wikipedia, a government circular, and an SEO content farm as roughly equal text.
For "what documents do I need for a passport," that is dangerous.
FOMOA scores sources explicitly (more on the ranking system below).
3. Hindi and Hinglish queries.
Roughly half of India's internet users are more comfortable in Hindi than English.
A query like "PM Kisan ka paisa kab aayega" should just work — no translation, no language toggle.
4. Government scheme navigation.
India runs 100+ central schemes and 1000+ state schemes.
Finding the one you qualify for, with the right documents and the official application link, is genuinely hard.
This is one of FOMOA's strongest use cases — covered in detail in FOMOA vs Exa.ai and India Use-Cases.
Next up: FOMOA's Core Features in 2026.
Native Hindi and Hinglish support.
FOMOA handles three modes with zero manual switching:
Pure Hindi (शुद्ध हिंदी) — full Devanagari queries and answers..
Hinglish — "Mujhe ek accha SIP plan batao for long term.".
Code-mixed — a sentence that swaps scripts mid-way..
It auto-detects the language and, importantly, expands Hindi queries to also search high-quality English sources, then answers back in the user's language.
On internal Hindi factual-query benchmarks this reached around 89% accuracy — a number that comes directly from how the model was trained (below).
150+ Indian authoritative sources.
FOMOA maintains a curated index of Indian government domains, regulators, and reputable publications, with Indian government domains (.gov.in, .nic.in) getting automatic trust.
So a scheme question is answered from the actual ministry page, not a third-party aggregator.
Indian number and format understanding.
Lakhs, crores, Indian financial-year dates, GST/PAN context — handled natively.
This sounds small until you watch a global model turn "₹2.5 crore" into "$2.5 million."
Government scheme navigator.
Ask in plain language ("schemes for women entrepreneurs in Maharashtra") and get eligibility, required documents, benefits, and the official application link — sourced from official portals.
Deep research mode.
For harder questions, FOMOA can follow leads across multiple "hops," detect conflicts between sources, and synthesise a cited report.
There are three depths — quick (~5s), normal (~15s), and deep (~60s).
The mechanics are explained in FOMOA for Developers.
Real-time information.
FOMOA pulls fresh data from its Indian source set rather than relying only on a training snapshot, so exam dates, scheme deadlines, and prices stay current.
Free, OpenAI-compatible API.
Developers can point the standard OpenAI SDK at FOMOA by changing the base_url — no rewrite required.
This is the feature that makes FOMOA interesting beyond consumer search.
Let's explore How FOMOA Ranks Results: The 4-Signal System.
The single most important thing separating FOMOA from "ask a chatbot" is that it ranks sources explicitly before answering.
Four signals combine into a score:
Signal, Weight, What it measures.
Semantic relevance, 50%, How well the source actually answers the query.
Source credibility, 25%, Authority of the domain (gov/regulator/established publisher → high).
Content freshness, 20%, How recent the information is.
Domain expertise, 5%, Topical match between source and query.
A couple of things make this practical:
Indian government domains get automatic trust.
A gov.in notification outranks a blog summarising it..
Weighting is query-adaptive.
For "latest NEET 2026 date," freshness matters more; for "what is compound interest," credibility and relevance dominate..
Conflicts are surfaced, not hidden.
When sources disagree, FOMOA shows the disagreement and the more authoritative source, instead of silently picking one..
This is the same instinct behind good engineering: don't treat all inputs as equal — score them, weight them, and make the decision auditable.
If you are interested in the broader landscape of AI search tools, I compared the options in the best free AI search engine for India.
Now let's look at How FOMOA Was Trained (86,000 India-Centric Samples).
FOMOA's India fluency is not a prompt trick — it is baked into the model weights.
The training approach, briefly:
Base model: Qwen2.5-7B-Instruct.
A 7B model was a deliberate choice — large enough to reason well, small enough to serve cheaply and stay free for users..
Method: QLoRA fine-tuning (4-bit quantised base + low-rank adapters), which makes fine-tuning a 7B model feasible on modest hardware..
Training data (≈86,000 samples):.
56,760 Hindi/Hinglish samples (about 65% of the mix) — this is why Hindi works natively rather than via translation..
20,000 analytical-reasoning samples..
10,000 diverse-knowledge samples..
Compute: roughly 113 hours of training..
The key lesson: native beats translated.
A model trained on real Hindi and Hinglish understands idiom and code-mixing in a way that a translate-then-answer pipeline never will.
That is the difference between "technically supports Hindi" and "actually feels Indian."
Now, let's talk about Who FOMOA Is For.
Students — exam dates, syllabus, cutoffs, and scholarships from official NTA/government sources..
Professionals — tax, finance, and policy questions answered in Indian units with cited sources..
Business owners — scheme and compliance discovery (MUDRA, GST, registrations)..
General users — government services, healthcare schemes, and everyday queries in their own language..
The student and government-scheme workflows are deep enough that I gave them their own guide: FOMOA vs Exa.ai and India Use-Cases.
Moving on to Getting Started.
Open FOMOA and ask a question in Hindi, English, or Hinglish..
Read the cited answer — every claim links back to its source so you can verify..
For deeper questions, switch to deep research mode..
Developers: grab an API key and read the developer guide..
Next up: Frequently Asked Questions.
Is FOMOA really completely free?
Yes — both the web interface and the developer API are free to use, which is the headline difference versus paid AI-search APIs.
How accurate is FOMOA for government information?
Government questions are answered from official gov.in/nic.in sources with citations, and those domains are automatically trusted in the ranking system.
Always verify deadlines and amounts against the linked official page before acting.
Does FOMOA work in Hindi?
Natively.
About 65% of its training data was Hindi/Hinglish, with ~89% accuracy on Hindi factual queries in internal benchmarks.
Can developers use it?
Yes.
It exposes an OpenAI-compatible endpoint plus India-specific endpoints for research, crawling, and entity search.
See the developer guide.
Let's explore The Takeaway.
FOMOA's bet is simple: India deserves AI that speaks its languages, trusts the right sources, and reads its numbers correctly — for free.
The credibility ranking and native Hindi training are what make that more than a marketing line.
Keep reading: FOMOA for Developers: OpenAI-Compatible API, Deep Research & Ethical Crawling.
FOMOA vs Exa.ai + India Use-Cases: Schemes, Students & Startups.
The Best Free AI Search Engine for India in 2026.
AI Capabilities in 2026: A Complete Guide.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.