You're listening to: FOMOA vs Exa.ai + India Use-Cases: Schemes, Students & Startups (2026).
Exa.ai charges ~$5 per 1,000 requests; FOMOA offers the same core capabilities free, with native Hindi and 150+ Indian sources.
Full comparison plus real India use-cases — government schemes, JEE/NEET/UPSC students, and startup data.
Let's get started.
There are two questions people actually ask about FOMOA.
The first is "how does it compare to the paid AI-search APIs like Exa.ai?"
The second is "what can I actually do with it in India?"
This guide answers both — the comparison first, then three concrete India use-cases: government schemes, student exam prep, and startup/company data.
For the product overview and developer reference, see the complete FOMOA guide and FOMOA for developers.
Now, let's talk about FOMOA vs Exa.ai.
Exa.ai is a strong, general-purpose AI-search API.
The two differences that matter for Indian builders are cost and India-tuning.
Capability, Exa.ai, FOMOA.
Pricing, ~$5 / 1,000 requests, Free.
Direct answers, ✅, ✅ (/api/answer).
Deep research, ✅, ✅ (/api/research, 3 hops).
Web crawling, ✅, ✅ (/api/crawl, robots-aware).
Entity search, ✅, ✅ (/api/entities).
Collections / websets, ✅, ✅.
Native Hindi/Hinglish, ❌, ✅.
150+ Indian sources, ❌, ✅.
Indian number/format awareness, ❌, ✅.
What this means in practice.
Cost at scale.
A startup running a news/research aggregator that makes, say, 100,000 requests a month pays real money on a per-request API and ₹0 on FOMOA.
For a student project or an early-stage product, free is decisive..
India context is built in, not bolted on.
Exa returns excellent general results; FOMOA additionally understands lakhs/crores, prioritises gov.in sources, and answers Hindi natively (about 65% of its training was Hindi/Hinglish — see the training breakdown)..
Migrating from Exa to FOMOA.
Because FOMOA's chat endpoint is OpenAI-compatible, migration is mostly URL and endpoint mapping:
Point your client at FOMOA's base_url..
Map Exa's search/contents calls to /api/answer, /api/research, and /api/crawl..
Adjust parameter names where they differ..
The full code-level walkthrough (LangChain, LlamaIndex, streaming) is in FOMOA for developers.
When to choose which.
Choose Exa.ai if you need a mature global index and your queries are not India-centric.
Choose FOMOA if your users are Indian, your budget is tight, or you need Hindi and government-source accuracy.
For most Indian products, FOMOA wins on both cost and relevance.
Now the part that makes FOMOA genuinely useful day-to-day: India use-cases.
Moving on to Use-Case 1: Government Schemes.
India runs 100+ central schemes and 1000+ state schemes.
The hard part is not the schemes — it is discovering which one you qualify for, with the right documents and the official link.
FOMOA's entity search and gov.in source priority make this its single strongest consumer workflow.
Ask in plain language (Hindi works best here
"Main ek chhota kisan hoon, mere liye kaun si scheme hai?".
"Schemes for women entrepreneurs in Maharashtra".
"Senior citizen pension scheme eligibility and documents".
You get eligibility, required documents, benefits, and the official application URL — pulled from official portals.
The major schemes people search for:
PM-KISAN — income support for farmers..
Ayushman Bharat (PM-JAY) — health cover for eligible families..
MUDRA loans — collateral-free business loans (Shishu/Kishore/Tarun)..
PM Awas Yojana — housing assistance..
Pro tips: ask state-specific questions (schemes differ by state), check eligibility before applying, and always confirm amounts and deadlines against the linked official page — FOMOA cites it precisely so you can.
Next up: Use-Case 2: Students (JEE, NEET, UPSC & Scholarships).
Exam information online is a minefield of outdated dates and coaching-center SEO.
FOMOA answers from official NTA and government sources, with citations, so students get the current number.
JEE Main 2026 — exam dates, session details, syllabus and pattern, and college cutoffs..
NEET 2026 — exam details and medical-college queries..
UPSC Civil Services 2026 — the exam calendar and optional-subject information..
Scholarships — national (NSP) and state scholarships with eligibility and deadlines..
How students should use it: ask specific questions ("NEET 2026 application last date"), verify every deadline against the cited official source, and use Hindi/Hinglish freely.
Set up a few recurring queries during application season so you never miss a window.
Let's explore Use-Case 3: Startup & Company Data.
For investors, job-seekers, and market researchers, FOMOA's /api/entities is a free window into 50,000+ Indian companies and startups, searchable by industry, location, and funding stage.
Investors — screen startups by sector and stage..
Job seekers — find funded companies hiring in a city..
Journalists & researchers — pull market and funding data with sources..
You can combine filters ("fintech, Bengaluru, Series A") or just ask in natural language.
The API mechanics are in FOMOA for developers.
Now let's look at The Bottom Line.
Against paid APIs, FOMOA's pitch is "the same core capabilities, free, and tuned for India."
Against doing nothing, its pitch is the three workflows above — schemes, exams, and company data — that are genuinely painful without it.
If your users are in India, it is worth the five-minute integration.
Keep reading: FOMOA AI: The Complete Guide (2026).
FOMOA for Developers: API, Deep Research & Ethical Crawling.
The Best Free AI Search Engine for India in 2026.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.