You're listening to: FOMOA for Developers: OpenAI-Compatible API, Deep Research & Ethical Crawling.
The complete FOMOA developer guide — a drop-in OpenAI-compatible endpoint, multi-hop deep research, an ethical web-crawl API that respects robots.txt, and entity search over 50,000+ Indian companies and schemes.
Let's get started.
If you have ever wired an app to the OpenAI API, you already know how to use FOMOA.
That is the whole point: FOMOA exposes an OpenAI-compatible endpoint, so you change one line — the base_url — and keep the rest of your code.
On top of that drop-in chat API, it adds India-optimised search plus four purpose-built endpoints for research, crawling, and entity lookup.
This guide consolidates the developer story: the compatible chat API, deep research, ethical crawling, and entity/company search.
For the product overview and how the model was trained, start with the complete FOMOA guide.
Now, let's talk about Drop-In OpenAI Replacement.
The migration is deliberately boring — which is exactly what you want:
Because it speaks the OpenAI wire format, it works with anything built on that format — the official SDK, LangChain, LlamaIndex, and your existing streaming code.
Streaming.
If you are designing the API layer around this, the usual rules apply — sensible status codes, idempotency, and backpressure.
I wrote those up in REST API design best practices and rate limiting & API gateway patterns.
Moving on to The India-Specific Endpoints.
Beyond /v1/chat/completions, FOMOA exposes four endpoints that a generic chat model does not give you:
Endpoint, Purpose.
/api/answer, A direct, cited answer to a single question.
/api/research, Multi-hop deep research with conflict detection.
/api/crawl, Ethical web-content extraction.
/api/entities, Structured search over Indian companies & schemes.
/api/answer — direct cited answers.
When you want a single grounded answer rather than a chat turn, /api/answer returns the response with its citations, so you can show users where each claim came from.
Next up: Deep Research: Multi-Hop, Conflict-Aware.
A normal search does one query and returns links.
Multi-hop research uses the results of the first search to decide what to search next — following leads the way a human researcher would — then synthesises a cited report and flags where sources disagree.
FOMOA offers three depths so you can trade latency for thoroughness:
Quick (~5s) — a fast single-pass answer..
Normal (~15s) — a couple of hops, good for most questions..
Deep (~60s) — up to three hops, conflict detection, and a structured report..
The conflicts[] array is the interesting part: instead of silently picking one number when two sources disagree, it returns both and tells you which source is more authoritative — the same credibility ranking described in the complete FOMOA guide.
This is what makes it usable for journalists, analysts, and anyone who has to defend an answer.
Let's explore Ethical Web Crawling.
/api/crawl extracts clean, readable content from a URL — but with guardrails that a naive scraper skips:
Respects robots.txt.
If a site disallows crawling, FOMOA does not crawl it..
Rate-limited to ~2 requests/second per site so you do not hammer anyone's server..
Returns clean text, links, and metadata rather than raw HTML soup..
It supports single-page, site-wide, and sitemap-based modes, handles pagination, and degrades gracefully on JavaScript-heavy pages.
The ethical defaults matter: building data pipelines on top of a crawler that ignores robots.txt is how you get your IPs blocked and your project shut down.
Now let's look at Entity Search: Indian Companies & Schemes.
/api/entities is structured search over India-specific entities — most usefully, 50,000+ Indian startups and companies and the catalogue of government schemes.
You can filter by industry, location, and funding stage (and combine them), or pass a natural-language query.
For the scheme side — eligibility, documents, official links — see the use-case walkthroughs in FOMOA vs Exa.ai + India Use-Cases.
Now, let's talk about Framework Integrations.
Because the chat endpoint is OpenAI-compatible, framework integration is trivial:
LlamaIndex works the same way — point its OpenAI-compatible LLM wrapper at FOMOA's base_url.
Moving on to Error Handling and Rate Limits.
Treat it like any production dependency:
Handle 429s with backoff.
Respect the documented per-key limits and retry with exponential backoff and jitter..
Set timeouts, especially for deep research (which can legitimately take ~60s)..
Cache repeated answers where freshness allows — the same caching discipline I cover in Redis caching strategies..
Next up: Why This Matters.
The combination is what is rare: an OpenAI-compatible chat API you can adopt in five minutes, plus research, crawl, and entity endpoints tuned for Indian data — at zero cost.
For a paid-vs-free breakdown against the main commercial alternative, read FOMOA vs Exa.ai.
Keep reading: FOMOA AI: The Complete Guide (2026).
FOMOA vs Exa.ai + India Use-Cases.
REST API Design Best Practices.
Rate Limiting & API Gateway Patterns.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.