You're listening to: GitHub Actions CI/CD: Complete Pipeline Setup Guide.
Build robust CI/CD pipelines with GitHub Actions.
Learn workflow syntax, testing automation, Docker builds, deployments to AWS/Vercel, secrets management, and advanced patterns for production systems.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
GitHub Actions has become the go-to CI/CD solution for modern development teams.
At Dr. Dangs Lab, we've built pipelines that automatically test, build, and deploy across multiple environments.
This guide covers everything from basics to advanced patterns.
Moving on to Workflow Basics.
Anatomy of a Workflow.
Trigger Events.
Next up: Complete CI Pipeline.
Testing and Linting.
Let's explore Docker Build and Push.
Now let's look at Deployment Workflows.
Deploy to AWS ECS.
Deploy to Vercel.
Now, let's talk about Matrix Builds.
Moving on to Reusable Workflows.
Creating a Reusable Workflow.
Using the Reusable Workflow.
Next up: Secrets and Environment Management.
Let's explore Advanced Patterns.
Conditional Jobs.
Caching Dependencies.
Notification on Failure.
Now let's look at Key Takeaways.
Start simple - Add complexity as needed.
Use caching - Speed up builds significantly.
Leverage matrix builds - Test across environments.
Create reusable workflows - DRY principle.
Secure secrets - Use environments and OIDC.
Monitor and alert - Know when things break.
Optimize for speed - Parallel jobs, caching.
Now, let's talk about Conclusion.
GitHub Actions provides a powerful, flexible CI/CD platform integrated directly into your repository.
Start with basic workflows, then gradually adopt advanced patterns like reusable workflows and matrix builds.
The key is to automate everything that can be automated.
Building CI/CD pipelines?
Connect on LinkedIn to discuss automation strategies.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.