You're listening to: Building Healthcare Technology at Dr. Dangs Lab: What They Don't Teach You.
3 years of building lab management systems taught me that healthcare software is nothing like regular SaaS.
Here's what actually matters when patient care depends on your code.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about My First Week Was a Reality Check.
I joined Dr. Dangs Lab thinking I knew how to build software.
I'd worked on e-commerce, fintech, the usual stuff.
Healthcare would be just another domain, right?
On my third day, a doctor called our support line furious.
A patient's critical test result was delayed by 4 hours because our notification system silently failed.
The patient had a serious condition that needed immediate attention.
Nobody was hurt, thankfully.
But I went home that night and couldn't sleep.
In my previous jobs, a bug meant someone's shopping cart didn't work.
Here, it could mean something much worse.
That's when I understood: healthcare software isn't about features.
It's about reliability, accuracy, and the weight of responsibility that comes with every line of code.
Moving on to What We Were Dealing With.
Dr. Dangs Lab is one of India's leading pathology centers.
When I arrived, the situation was:
15+ collection centers across Delhi NCR sending samples to central labs.
Thousands of patients daily expecting accurate, timely reports.
80+ doctors and lab technicians depending on our systems.
Legacy software that crashed during peak hours.
Paper-based workflows causing 2-3 hour delays in report delivery.
No real-time tracking - patients calling repeatedly asking "where's my report?".
The previous system was a PHP monolith from 2010.
It worked... mostly.
But as patient volume grew, it started buckling.
Reports got delayed.
Data got lost.
Staff were frustrated.
My job: rebuild it without breaking anything.
Next up: The Architecture We Built (After 3 Rewrites).
I'm not going to pretend we got it right the first time.
The current system is version 3, and each previous version taught us something painful.
Why These Specific Choices.
FastAPI for most services: Our team knew Python well.
Healthcare has complex business logic that changes frequently.
We needed to move fast on new features.
The auto-generated API docs saved hours of documentation work.
Go for report processing: Generating 500 PDFs simultaneously in Python?
Forget it.
Memory usage was unpredictable with Python's PDF libraries.
Go gave us 15x performance improvement (I wrote about this in my microservices article).
PostgreSQL, not MySQL or MongoDB: ACID compliance isn't optional when dealing with medical data.
The JSONB columns let us handle semi-structured lab results without schema migrations every week.
Row-level security for multi-tenant data isolation.
Redis for more than just caching: Real-time sample tracking (pub/sub).
Rate limiting (patients refreshing "where's my report?"
50 times).
Session management with automatic expiry.
Task queues for async processing.
Let's explore The Hardest Problems We Solved.
Problem 1: Sample Tracking Without Losing Anything.
A sample travels through multiple hands: Collected at a center.
Transported to lab (could take hours).
Received at lab.
Processed.
Results entered.
Report generated.
Delivered to patient.
If ANY step fails silently, someone's diagnosis gets delayed.
Problem 2: Report Generation at Scale.
On busy days, we generate 3,000+ reports.
Each report is a multi-page PDF with: Patient demographics.
Test results with reference ranges.
Interpretation notes.
Doctor's signature (digital).
QR code for verification.
Our first approach (synchronous, one-by-one) took 6 hours on peak days.
Patients were furious.
Problem 3: The "Where's My Report?"
Problem.
Patients would call 10-20 times asking for their report status.
Our support team was overwhelmed.
We built real-time tracking:
Now let's look at Healthcare-Specific Lessons (The Hard Way).
1. Audit Everything.
No, Really, Everything..
2. Lab Equipment Integration is a Nightmare.
Modern analyzers speak HL7 (a healthcare data format from the 1980s).
Parsing it is... an experience.
3. Downtime is Not an Option.
Now, let's talk about The Results After 2 Years.
What Changed, Before, After.
Report delivery time, 24-48 hours, 4-6 hours (90% under 2 hrs).
Daily support calls, 200+, ~30.
System downtime/month, 4-5 hours, <5 minutes.
Data entry errors, ~5%, <0.5%.
Patient satisfaction score, No data, 4.6/5.
But the number I'm most proud of: zero data breaches, zero lost samples, zero incorrect reports in production.
Moving on to What I Wish Someone Had Told Me.
Healthcare moves slowly for good reasons.
Doctors and lab techs have workflows burned into muscle memory.
Change needs to be gradual..
Regulations aren't obstacles, they're guardrails.
HIPAA-like requirements forced us to build better systems than we would have otherwise..
Paper isn't going away.
Many doctors still want printed reports.
Design for hybrid workflows..
Every error message might be read by a panicking patient.
"Report generation failed" causes anxiety.
"Your report is being prepared and will be ready in 30 minutes" is better..
The people using your software are exhausted.
Lab techs work 10-hour shifts.
Make the UI obvious.
Reduce clicks.
Don't make them think..
Building healthcare software changed how I think about engineering.
Speed matters, but accuracy matters more.
Features are nice, but reliability is essential.
And at the end of the day, there's a patient waiting for results that might change their life.
If you're considering healthcare tech, know that it's harder than regular SaaS - but also more meaningful.
Every optimization you make helps real people get better care.
Working on healthcare systems?
I'd love to hear about your experiences.
Connect on LinkedIn or check out my other technical articles.
Next up: Related Articles.
Building Scalable Microservices - The technical deep-dive.
PostgreSQL Performance Optimization - How we handle millions of records.
WebSocket Real-time Applications - The patient tracking system.
Event-Driven Architecture with Kafka - Decoupling our services.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.