You're listening to: Idempotency Keys: How We Stopped Double-Charging Customers.
A retry on a slow payment request charged a customer twice.
A practical guide to idempotency keys — how to design the key, store it atomically, handle in-flight duplicates, and make any unsafe POST safe to retry.
Let's get started.
The email I never want to receive: "I was charged twice for one order."
We looked, and it was true — two identical payments, eight seconds apart, same amount, same customer.
No bug in our charging logic.
No double-click.
The customer pressed "Pay" exactly once.
The cause was a retry — and it is one of the most common, most expensive bugs in distributed systems.
The fix is idempotency keys.
This post is the practical version: how the double-charge happens, and how to make any unsafe operation safe to repeat.
It builds on ideas in REST API design best practices and rate limiting & API gateway patterns.
Now, let's talk about How one click becomes two charges.
Here is the timeline of our incident:
The client POSTs /payments to charge ₹2,000..
Our server receives it, calls the payment gateway, the charge succeeds..
While we are writing the success response, the request takes longer than the client's 10-second timeout..
The client gives up, sees a timeout, and — being a well-behaved client — retries the same request..
Our server receives the retry as a brand-new request, calls the gateway again, charges ₹2,000 a second time..
Nobody did anything wrong.
The network was slow once.
The deadly combination is a non-idempotent operation + an automatic retry.
And retries are everywhere: client libraries retry, load balancers retry, mobile apps retry on flaky connections.
If your "create payment" endpoint isn't safe to call twice, it is only a matter of time.
Moving on to What "idempotent" means.
An operation is idempotent if performing it multiple times has the same effect as performing it once.
GET, PUT, and DELETE are idempotent by definition in HTTP.
POST is not — and "charge a card" is the canonical non-idempotent operation.
You cannot change the semantics of "charge a card."
But you can attach a token that lets the server recognize a retry and refuse to do the work twice.
That token is the idempotency key.
Next up: The design: a client-generated key.
The client generates a unique key (a UUID) for each logical operation and sends it with the request.
Crucially, a retry reuses the same key.
The server stores the key and the result; if it sees the key again, it returns the stored result instead of re-executing.
This is exactly how Stripe, PayPal, and every serious payments API work.
The key belongs to the operation, not the attempt — so the first try and every retry carry the same key.
Let's explore The naive implementation (and its race condition).
The obvious version:
This is better, but it has a race.
Two requests with the same key can both pass the find(key) check before either inserts — and you are back to double-charging.
The "check, then act" gap is the bug.
You must make claiming the key atomic.
Now let's look at The correct implementation.
Use a unique constraint and let the database arbitrate.
Insert the key first, in a PENDING state, before doing any work.
The unique constraint guarantees exactly one winner.
Three cases are now handled correctly:
First request: claims the key, charges once, stores the result..
Retry after completion: unique-violation → finds completed → replays the stored response.
No second charge..
Concurrent duplicate (original still running): unique-violation → finds pending → returns 409, so the client backs off and retries, eventually getting the replayed result..
That in-flight case is the one the naive version misses, and it is exactly the 8-seconds-apart scenario that bit us.
Now, let's talk about Details that matter in production.
Scope the key to the request.
Store a hash of the request body alongside the key.
If the same key arrives with a different body, that is a client bug — reject it (422) rather than silently replaying an unrelated result.
Set a TTL.
Idempotency keys don't need to live forever.
We expire them after 24 hours, which comfortably covers any realistic retry window.
A periodic job (or a Redis TTL, if you store keys there) handles cleanup.
Pick the right storage.
Redis with SET key value NX EX 86400 is a great fit for the atomic claim and the TTL — the same NX single-flight trick I used to stop a cache stampede.
A relational table with a unique constraint is just as correct and gives you durability for free.
Either works; the non-negotiable property is atomic claim.
Return the key boundary clearly.
Document that clients must generate one key per operation and reuse it on retry.
An idempotency system only works if clients hold up their half of the contract.
Moving on to Where else to apply this.
Once you have the pattern, you start seeing non-idempotent endpoints everywhere: "send invitation email," "create order," "submit insurance claim," "publish event."
Any POST that has a side effect and might be retried should accept an idempotency key.
It is cheap insurance against the most embarrassing class of bug — doing something irreversible twice.
Next up: The takeaway.
Retries are not a failure of your clients; they are a feature of resilient systems, and they are not going away.
The server's job is to make repetition harmless.
An idempotency key + an atomic claim + a stored result turns "charge the card" — the scariest operation in the system — into something you can safely call as many times as the network demands.
We shipped this, replayed the failure in staging (slow response + client retry), and watched it charge exactly once.
The double-charge emails stopped.
Related reading: REST API Design Best Practices.
Rate Limiting & API Gateway Patterns.
The Cache Stampede That Took Down Our API: A Redis p99 War Story.
Event-Driven Architecture with Kafka.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.