You're listening to: Kubernetes Advanced: Operators, Helm, and Service Mesh Guide.
Master advanced Kubernetes concepts including Helm charts, custom operators, service mesh with Istio, GitOps patterns, and production best practices.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
Once you've mastered basic Kubernetes deployments, the next level involves Helm for package management, Operators for complex application lifecycle management, and Service Mesh for advanced networking.
These tools are essential for running production workloads at scale.
In this guide, we'll cover: Helm charts creation and best practices.
Kubernetes Operators with Operator SDK.
Service Mesh with Istio.
GitOps with ArgoCD.
Production patterns and optimization.
Moving on to Helm Charts Deep Dive.
Chart Structure.
Chart.yaml.
Templates with Best Practices.
values.yaml.
Helm Commands.
Next up: Kubernetes Operators.
Operator Pattern.
Custom Resource Definition.
Controller (Go).
Let's explore Service Mesh with Istio.
Architecture.
Traffic Management.
mTLS Configuration.
Now let's look at GitOps with ArgoCD.
Application Definition.
ApplicationSet for Multi-Environment.
Now, let's talk about Production Best Practices.
Resource Management.
Pod Disruption Budget.
Moving on to Conclusion.
Advanced Kubernetes features enable: Helm: Standardized, versioned deployments.
Operators: Automated application management.
Service Mesh: Secure, observable microservices.
GitOps: Declarative, auditable infrastructure.
Mastering these tools is essential for production Kubernetes at scale.
Next up: Related Articles.
Docker & Kubernetes Deployment Guide - K8s fundamentals.
GitHub Actions CI/CD Complete Guide - CI/CD pipelines.
Apache Kafka Deep Dive - Event streaming.
Microservices with Go and FastAPI - Build microservices.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.