You're listening to: MCP vs Direct API Calls: The Token-Efficiency Debate (2026).
MCP exploded to 10,000+ servers, but in 2026 many teams are moving back to direct API calls and CLIs over token cost — ~200 tokens per CLI command vs 32,000–82,000 for MCP.
A clear-eyed breakdown of when MCP is worth it and when it isn't.
Let's get started.
The Model Context Protocol (MCP) was the breakout backend story of 2025 — by late that year there were 10,000+ public MCP servers, and "just wrap it in an MCP server" became the default way to give an AI agent a new capability.
But in 2026 the conversation has flipped in a way worth paying attention to: a growing number of teams are quietly moving away from MCP and back to direct API calls and CLIs, and the reason is almost entirely about tokens.
This post lays out the trade-off honestly, because the answer isn't "MCP good" or "MCP bad" — it's "MCP has a fixed cost that only pays off above a certain scale."
If you're building agent backends (see building backends for AI agents), this is one of the more consequential architecture calls you'll make this year.
Now, let's talk about What MCP actually gives you.
MCP is a standardized interface that lets an agent discover and call tools, query data, and coordinate across vendors without bespoke per-integration glue.
Its genuine wins:
Standardization.
One protocol; an agent that speaks MCP can use any MCP server..
Discovery.
The agent can ask a server what tools it offers and how to call them..
Decoupling.
Tool providers and agent builders integrate against the protocol, not each other..
That's real value, and for an ecosystem of interoperable tools it's the right abstraction.
The catch is what discovery costs.
Moving on to The token problem.
Here's the number that's driving the 2026 rethink.
To use an MCP server, the agent loads the server's tool definitions — names, descriptions, full JSON schemas for every tool — into its context.
For a rich server, that's 32,000 to 82,000 tokens before the agent does anything.
Every turn that context is re-sent or cached, and if an agent has several MCP servers attached, the tool definitions alone can dominate the context window.
Compare that to a CLI.
Teaching an agent to run a command-line tool costs roughly 200 tokens — the agent already knows how to call shells, and a --help is far smaller than a full schema dump.
A direct HTTP call is similar: a few hundred tokens for an endpoint description.
Approach, Approx. tokens to "equip" the agent, Best when.
MCP server, 32,000–82,000 (tool schemas in context), Many interoperable tools, cross-vendor, discovery matters.
CLI command, ~200 per command, Token budget is tight, tools are known and stable.
Direct API call, a few hundred per endpoint, A handful of known endpoints, full control.
When token efficiency matters — and at 2026 inference prices, it almost always does — that's a 100–400× difference in setup cost.
Multiply by every turn of a long agent run and the economics get loud.
Next up: So when is MCP actually worth it?.
MCP's fixed cost amortizes when the value of standardization and discovery outweighs the per-context token tax.
Reach for MCP when:
You're exposing tools to agents you don't control — third parties, many clients, an ecosystem.
The interop is the whole point..
The tool set is large and changes often, so runtime discovery genuinely saves integration work..
Cross-vendor coordination is a core requirement and bespoke integrations would be unmanageable..
Reach for direct API calls or a CLI when:
You control both the agent and the backend.
You don't need discovery; you already know the tools..
Token budget is the constraint — long runs, cost-sensitive workloads, small context windows..
The tool set is small and stable.
A handful of endpoints don't justify schema-dump overhead..
Latency and simplicity matter more than protocol elegance..
A useful rule of thumb I've landed on: MCP is an ecosystem play; direct calls are a product play.
If you're building a platform for others to integrate with, MCP's standardization earns its tokens.
If you're shipping your own agent against your own backend, direct calls are usually leaner and easier to reason about.
Let's explore A hybrid that works.
You don't have to pick globally.
A pattern I like: direct/CLI for your hot-path, high-frequency tools (where token cost compounds), and MCP for the long tail of occasional, third-party, or discovery-heavy tools.
Keep the three tools the agent calls constantly as cheap direct functions; let the fifty tools it calls once a month live behind MCP.
You get interop where it helps and efficiency where it counts.
Whichever you choose, the backend reliability rules don't change.
An agent calling a tool via MCP or via a direct HTTP call has the same failure modes — it will retry, loop, and act on stale state — so the idempotency, durable-state, and run-scoped rate-limiting patterns apply identically.
The transport is a cost-and-interop decision; correctness is a separate, non-negotiable layer underneath it.
And for tools that kick off long work, route them through async, long-running APIs regardless of protocol.
Now let's look at The takeaway.
MCP isn't dead — it's maturing into what it's actually good for: standardized, discoverable, cross-vendor tool ecosystems.
What's changed in 2026 is that teams stopped reaching for it reflexively and started doing the token math.
If you control both ends and your tools are known and stable, direct calls or a CLI will usually serve your agent for a tiny fraction of the context cost.
Measure the tokens, not the hype, and let the bill decide.
Related reading: Building Backends for AI Agents: Idempotency, Retries & State.
Designing Async, Long-Running APIs for AI Agents.
REST API Design Best Practices.
AI-Native Backend Architecture for 2026.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.