You're listening to: Message Queues: RabbitMQ vs Redis Streams vs Kafka - Complete Comparison.
Deep comparison of RabbitMQ, Redis Streams, and Apache Kafka for message queuing.
Performance benchmarks, use cases, and production patterns for choosing the right message broker.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
Message queues are the backbone of distributed systems, enabling asynchronous communication, load leveling, and service decoupling.
But choosing between RabbitMQ, Redis Streams, and Apache Kafka isn't straightforward—each has distinct strengths.
Having implemented all three in production healthcare systems at Dr. Dangs Lab, I'll share real-world insights on when to use each technology.
Moving on to Architecture Comparison.
RabbitMQ - Traditional Message Broker.
Redis Streams - Lightweight & F
Apache Kafka - Distributed Log.
Next up: Performance Benchmarks.
Throughput Test (Messages/Second).
Latency Test (P99 in milliseconds).
Let's explore Implementation Examples.
RabbitMQ with Python (aio-pika).
Redis Streams with Python.
Apache Kafka with Python (aiokafka).
Now let's look at Comparison Matrix.
Feature, RabbitMQ, Redis Streams, Kafka.
Throughput, Medium (25K/s), High (100K/s), Very High (500K/s).
Latency, Low (1-5ms), Very Low (<1ms), Medium (2-8ms).
Ordering, Per queue, Per stream, Per partition.
Persistence, Disk + mirroring, RDB/AOF, Distributed log.
Replay, No (consumed once), Yes, Yes.
Routing, Complex (exchanges), Basic, Partitioning.
Scaling, Clustering, Cluster, Native horizontal.
Operations, Moderate, Simple, Complex.
Use Case, Task queues, RPC, Caching + streaming, Event sourcing, analytics.
Now, let's talk about When to Use Each.
RabbitMQ.
Redis Streams.
Apache Kafka.
Moving on to Production Patterns.
Dead Letter Queue Pattern.
Exactly-Once Processing.
Next up: Conclusion.
Each message queue has its sweet spot:
RabbitMQ: Best for traditional messaging with complex routing needs.
Redis Streams: Best for low-latency, simple streaming with existing Redis.
Kafka: Best for high-throughput event streaming and event sourcing.
In my healthcare systems, I use: Kafka for audit logs and event sourcing (immutable, replayable).
RabbitMQ for task queues with priority (lab test processing).
Redis Streams for real-time notifications (low latency).
Choose based on your specific requirements, not hype.
Let's explore Related Articles.
Apache Kafka Event Streaming Deep Dive - Kafka internals.
Event-Driven Architecture with Kafka - Event patterns.
Redis Caching Strategies - Redis patterns.
Building Scalable Microservices - Service architecture.
System Design Interview Guide - Architecture patterns.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.