You're listening to: ML-KEM vs ML-DSA: NIST's Post-Quantum Standards Explained.
ML-KEM (FIPS 203) and ML-DSA (FIPS 204) solve two different problems — key exchange vs digital signatures.
A clear, developer-focused explainer on what each does, their security levels, key and signature sizes, and when to use which.
Let's get started.
When teams start their post-quantum journey, the first confusion is almost always the same: "Do I need ML-KEM or ML-DSA?"
The short answer is usually both — because they solve two completely different problems.
ML-KEM gets two parties a shared secret.
ML-DSA proves who signed something.
Confusing them is like confusing Diffie-Hellman with RSA signatures: related field, different jobs.
This is the developer-focused explainer.
For the bigger picture of how to migrate, read the practical PQC migration guide first.
Now, let's talk about The two problems cryptography has to solve.
Almost all public-key cryptography exists to do one of two things:
Agree on a shared secret over an insecure channel — so two parties can then use fast symmetric encryption (AES).
Classically: Diffie-Hellman / ECDH, or RSA key transport..
Prove authenticity and integrity — that a message came from a specific party and wasn't tampered with.
Classically: RSA or ECDSA/Ed25519 signatures..
Quantum computers (via Shor's algorithm) break the classical answer to both.
NIST standardized a replacement for each:
ML-KEM (FIPS 203) → problem 1, key exchange..
ML-DSA (FIPS 204) → problem 2, signatures..
Both are built on module lattices — the "ML" prefix — whose security rests on the hardness of lattice problems (Module-LWE / Module-SIS) believed to resist both classical and quantum attack.
Moving on to ML-KEM: the key exchange (FIPS 203, formerly Kyber).
ML-KEM is a Key Encapsulation Mechanism.
The flow is slightly different from Diffie-Hellman, so it's worth seeing:
Alice generates a keypair and sends Bob her public key..
Bob runs encapsulate(public_key), which produces two things: a shared secret and a ciphertext.
Bob keeps the secret, sends Alice the ciphertext..
Alice runs decapsulate(ciphertext, private_key) and recovers the same shared secret..
Now both sides hold an identical secret that never crossed the wire, and they switch to AES-256 for bulk encryption.
ML-KEM comes in three parameter sets keyed to NIST security categories:
Parameter set, NIST level, Roughly comparable to.
ML-KEM-512, Category 1, AES-128.
ML-KEM-768, Category 3, AES-192.
ML-KEM-1024, Category 5, AES-256.
ML-KEM-768 is the common default — a strong balance of security and size, and what many TLS hybrid deployments use today.
Next up: ML-DSA: the signature (FIPS 204, formerly Dilithium).
ML-DSA is a digital signature scheme — the quantum-safe replacement for ECDSA/Ed25519/RSA signatures.
The shape is familiar:
sign(private_key, message) → signature.
verify(public_key, message, signature) → valid / invalid.
You use it anywhere you sign today: tokens (this is what makes QAuth quantum-safe), certificates, code/firmware signing, and software releases.
Its parameter sets:
Parameter set, NIST level.
ML-DSA-44, Category 2.
ML-DSA-65, Category 3.
ML-DSA-87, Category 5.
ML-DSA-65 is the typical default for general-purpose signing.
Let's explore The thing that surprises everyone: the sizes.
Lattice cryptography is fast, but it is big.
This is the practical cost that shapes real deployments.
Approximate sizes:
Scheme, Public key, "Payload", vs classical.
Ed25519 (classical), 32 B, 64 B signature, baseline.
X25519 (classical KEM-ish), 32 B, 32 B, baseline.
ML-KEM-768, ~1,184 B, ~1,088 B ciphertext, ~30–40× larger.
ML-DSA-65, ~1,952 B, ~3,300 B signature, ~50× larger signature.
Read that again: an ML-DSA-65 signature is several kilobytes versus 64 bytes for Ed25519.
The algorithms are computationally fast — often competitive with RSA — but the bytes on the wire are the real engineering consideration.
It inflates:
Tokens — a signed token jumps from a few hundred bytes to several KB..
TLS handshakes — bigger key-exchange and certificate messages..
Certificates — larger public keys and signatures..
For high-QPS APIs or bandwidth-constrained clients (IoT, mobile in low-connectivity regions), measure this.
It rarely blocks adoption, but it absolutely changes your latency and bandwidth budgets.
Now let's look at When to use which — a decision cheat sheet.
Establishing a secure channel / session key?
ML-KEM.
(TLS, VPNs, encrypting data for a recipient.).
Proving who created or approved something?
ML-DSA.
(Tokens, certificates, code signing, document signing.).
Building auth like QAuth?
both: ML-KEM to protect the channel/payload, ML-DSA to sign the token..
Need maximum conservatism for a root of trust / firmware?
consider SLH-DSA (FIPS 205), a hash-based signature with very large signatures but a security argument resting only on hash functions..
Now, let's talk about A note on hybrids.
In practice you rarely deploy these alone in 2026.
The recommended rollout pairs each with a classical algorithm — X25519 + ML-KEM for key exchange, Ed25519 + ML-DSA for signatures — so you're protected if either the classical or the post-quantum scheme is later broken.
The reasoning is in why hybrid Ed25519 + ML-DSA is the safe path.
Moving on to The takeaway.
Keep the two jobs straight and the rest follows: ML-KEM = key exchange, ML-DSA = signatures.
Default to ML-KEM-768 and ML-DSA-65 unless you have a specific reason to go higher or lower, budget for kilobyte-scale keys and signatures, and deploy them in hybrid mode.
Get those choices right and you have the cryptographic core of a quantum-safe system.
Related reading: Migrating to Post-Quantum Cryptography: A Practical Developer Guide (2026).
Hybrid Cryptography: Why Ed25519 + ML-DSA Is the Safe Migration Path.
QuantumShield: Building a Post-Quantum Cryptography Library from Scratch.
QAuth: The Post-Quantum Authentication Protocol.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.