You're listening to: Nginx Reverse Proxy and Load Balancing: Complete Production Guide.
Master Nginx configuration for reverse proxy, load balancing, SSL termination, caching, and rate limiting.
Learn production-ready configurations with practical examples and performance optimization.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
Nginx powers over 30% of all websites and is the go-to solution for reverse proxying and load balancing.
At Dr. Dangs Lab, Nginx handles millions of requests daily, routing traffic across our microservices.
This guide covers everything from basics to production-ready configurations.
Moving on to Nginx Architecture.
Next up: Basic Reverse Proxy.
Simple Configuration.
Reverse Proxy Configuration.
Let's explore Load Balancing.
Round Robin (Default).
Weighted Load Balancing.
Least Connections.
IP Hash (Session Persistence).
Health Checks and Failover.
Now let's look at Advanced Configurations.
Rate Limiting.
Caching.
WebSocket Support.
Static File Serving.
Security Headers.
Now, let's talk about Microservices Routing.
Moving on to Docker and Kubernetes.
Docker Compose Example.
Kubernetes Ingress.
Next up: Monitoring and Debugging.
Enable Status Module.
Debug Logging.
Testing Configuration.
Let's explore Performance Optimization.
Now let's look at Key Takeaways.
Use upstream blocks for load balancing flexibility.
Enable keepalive between Nginx and backends.
Configure health checks for automatic failover.
Implement rate limiting to protect services.
Cache static content aggressively.
Use SSL termination at Nginx level.
Monitor with stub_status and logs.
Test configuration before reload.
Now, let's talk about Conclusion.
Nginx is an incredibly powerful tool for reverse proxying and load balancing.
Start with basic configurations, then add features like caching, rate limiting, and health checks as your needs grow.
The key is to understand your traffic patterns and optimize accordingly.
Building scalable infrastructure?
Connect on LinkedIn to discuss architecture patterns.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.