You're listening to: Observability Stack: Prometheus, Grafana & Jaeger Complete Guide.
Build production-grade observability with Prometheus metrics, Grafana dashboards, and Jaeger distributed tracing.
Complete setup guide with alerting, custom metrics, and troubleshooting patterns.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
You can't fix what you can't see.
In distributed systems, observability isn't a luxury—it's survival.
When a healthcare platform serving millions of patients experiences a latency spike at 2 AM, you need answers in seconds, not hours.
This guide covers the three pillars of observability: Metrics (Prometheus), Visualization (Grafana), and Distributed Tracing (Jaeger).
I'll share production patterns from building HIPAA-compliant systems that demand 99.99% uptime.
Moving on to The Three Pillars of Observability.
Next up: Setting Up Prometheus.
Docker Compose Setup.
Prometheus Configuration.
Let's explore Instrumenting Python Applications.
FastAPI with Prometheus Metrics.
Business Metrics.
Now let's look at Distributed Tracing with Jaeger.
OpenTelemetry Setup.
Trace Context Propagation.
Now, let's talk about Grafana Dashboards.
API Performance Dashboard.
Database Dashboard Queries.
Moving on to Alerting Rules.
AlertManager Configuration.
Next up: SLO/SLI Implementation.
Let's explore Conclusion.
A robust observability stack is essential for operating reliable distributed systems:
Prometheus for time-series metrics and alerting.
Grafana for visualization and dashboards.
Jaeger for distributed tracing across services.
Key takeaways: Instrument early, not after problems occur.
Use business metrics alongside technical metrics.
Set up SLOs and error budgets.
Create runbooks linked to alerts.
Practice observability-driven development.
This stack has helped me maintain 99.99% uptime for healthcare systems where reliability isn't optional.
Now let's look at Related Articles.
Docker Kubernetes Deployment Guide - Container orchestration.
Building Scalable Microservices - Service architecture.
Redis Caching Strategies - Performance optimization.
GitHub Actions CI/CD Guide - Deployment pipelines.
PostgreSQL Performance Optimization - Database monitoring.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.