You're listening to: PSQA: Phonon-Mediated Silicon Carbide Quantum Architecture - A Novel Path to 1 Million Qubits.
Introducing PSQA - a revolutionary quantum computing architecture combining silicon carbide color centers, phononic crystal waveguides, and optical interconnects for scalable room-temperature quantum computing.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about PSQA: Phonon-Mediated Silicon Carbide Quantum Architecture.
Moving on to A Novel Path to 1 Million Qubits at Room Temperature.
This document introduces PSQA (Phonon-mediated Silicon Carbide Quantum Architecture) - an original quantum computing architecture designed from first principles to achieve unprecedented scalability while operating at room temperature.
Unlike existing approaches that are incremental improvements on established paradigms, PSQA represents a fundamental reimagining of how to build a practical, scalable quantum computer.
Next up: Executive Summary: Why PSQA is Different.
Let's explore Part 1: The Core Innovation.
1.1 Why Silicon Carbide Over Diamond?.
While our previous blog series focused on NV centers in diamond, PSQA uses Silicon Carbide (SiC) for compelling reasons:
1.2 The Key Insight: Phononic Coupling.
Here's what makes PSQA truly novel: We use acoustic phonons, not photons or direct coupling, for qubit-qubit interactions.
1.3 The Three-Layer Architecture.
PSQA uses a hierarchical three-layer architecture:
Now let's look at Part 2: The Physics Deep Dive.
2.1 Silicon Vacancy (V_Si) in 4H-SiC.
Our qubit is the negatively charged silicon vacancy (V_Si⁻) in 4H polytype silicon carbide:
2.2 Spin-Phonon Coupling Mechanism.
The key innovation: using phonons (quantized sound waves) to couple qubits:
2.3 Optical Spin Readout and Initialization.
Now, let's talk about Part 3: Fabrication and Scalability.
3.1 CMOS-Compatible Fabrication Process.
3.2 Scaling to 1 Million Qubits.
Moving on to Part 4: Error Correction Strategy.
4.1 Tailored Surface Code for PSQA.
Next up: Part 5: Performance Projections.
5.1 Gate Fidelities and Speed.
5.2 Comparison with Other Approaches.
Let's explore Part 6: Implementation Roadmap.
6.1 Development Phases.
6.2 Cost Breakdown.
Now let's look at Part 7: Why This Hasn't Been Done Before.
7.1 The Gap We're Filling.
Now, let's talk about Conclusion: The Path Forward.
PSQA represents a fundamentally different approach to building a quantum computer.
By combining:
Silicon Carbide color centers for CMOS compatibility.
Phononic crystal waveguides for scalable qubit coupling.
Optical interconnects for modular system scaling.
Room temperature operation for practical deployment.
We can potentially achieve what others cannot: a million-qubit quantum computer that doesn't require a power plant to operate or a PhD to maintain.
The path is challenging but achievable.
The physics is sound.
The engineering is demanding but within reach.
And the potential payoff - practical quantum computing accessible to organizations beyond just governments and tech giants - is worth the effort.
Moving on to References and Further Reading.
V_Si in SiC: Widmann et al., "Coherent control of single spins in silicon carbide at room temperature" Nature Materials (2015).
Phononic Crystals: Safavi-Naeini et al., "Two-dimensional phononic-photonic band gap optomechanical crystal cavity" Physical Review Letters (2014).
Spin-Phonon Coupling: Lemonde et al., "Phonon Networks with Silicon-Vacancy Centers in Diamond Waveguides" Physical Review Letters (2018).
SiC Photonics: Lukin et al., "4H-silicon-carbide-on-insulator for integrated quantum and nonlinear photonics" Nature Photonics (2020).
Surface Code: Fowler et al., "Surface codes: Towards practical large-scale quantum computation" Physical Review A (2012).
This document represents original research and architecture design.
While individual components have been studied, the specific combination presented here (V_Si + phononic coupling + hierarchical modular architecture) is novel and has not been previously published.
Document Version: 1.0 Date: February 2026 Author: Tushar Agrawal Classification: Public Technical Specification
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.