You're listening to: PM2 & Linux Services: Production Node.js Deployment Guide.
Complete guide to deploying Node.js applications in production using PM2 process manager and Linux systemd services.
Learn cluster mode, zero-downtime deployments, and monitoring.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
Running Node.js applications in production requires robust process management to handle crashes, enable zero-downtime deployments, and utilize multiple CPU cores effectively.
Two primary approaches dominate the Linux ecosystem: PM2 (a Node.js-specific process manager) and systemd (the Linux system and service manager).
In this guide, we'll explore: PM2 fundamentals and advanced features.
Linux systemd service creation and management.
When to use each approach.
Production-ready configurations.
Monitoring and logging strategies.
Moving on to PM2 Fundamentals.
Installation and Basic Usage.
Starting Applications.
Process Management Commands.
Next up: PM2 Cluster Mode.
PM2's cluster mode allows you to run multiple instances of your Node.js application, utilizing all available CPU cores:
Starting in Cluster Mode.
Cluster Mode Application Example.
Let's explore PM2 Ecosystem File.
The ecosystem file (ecosystem.config.js) is the recommended way to configure PM2 applications:
Using the Ecosystem File.
Now let's look at Linux systemd Services.
systemd is the default init system on most modern Linux distributions and provides a powerful way to manage services.
systemd Service File Structure.
Managing systemd Services.
Running PM2 Under systemd.
The best practice is to run PM2 itself under systemd:
Generated systemd file for PM2:
Now, let's talk about PM2 vs systemd: When to Use Which.
Use PM2 When:.
Running Node.js applications exclusively.
Need cluster mode for multi-core utilization.
Want built-in zero-downtime reloads.
Prefer simple deployment workflows.
Need log rotation and management.
Want a web dashboard (PM2 Plus).
Use systemd When:.
Running multiple types of services (not just Node.js).
Need comprehensive security hardening.
Want tight resource controls (cgroups, memory limits).
Managing system-level services.
Need complex service dependencies.
Prefer native Linux tooling.
Use Both (PM2 under systemd):.
Best of both worlds.
PM2 handles Node.js specifics (clustering, reloads).
systemd handles boot persistence and supervision.
Most production-ready approach.
Moving on to Zero-Downtime Deployments.
PM2 Zero-Downtime Reload.
How it works:
Graceful Shutdown Implementation.
PM2 Configuration for Graceful Shutdown.
Next up: Log Management.
PM2 Log Commands.
systemd Journal Logging.
Structured Logging for Production.
Let's explore Monitoring and Metrics.
PM2 Built-in Monitoring.
PM2 Plus (Paid Service).
Custom Metrics with PM2.
Prometheus Metrics Export.
Now let's look at Running Multiple Applications.
PM2 Multiple Apps.
systemd Multiple Services.
Creating a target for all services:
Now, let's talk about Security Best Practices.
PM2 Security.
systemd Security Hardening.
Moving on to Complete Production Setup.
Here's a complete setup combining PM2 with systemd:
Next up: Conclusion.
Both PM2 and systemd are excellent tools for running Node.js applications in production.
The key takeaways:
PM2 excels at Node.js-specific features: clustering, zero-downtime reloads, and built-in monitoring.
systemd provides robust system-level service management with comprehensive security hardening.
The combination of both (PM2 under systemd) is the most production-ready approach.
Always implement graceful shutdown for zero-downtime deployments.
Use structured logging and metrics for observability.
At Dr Dangs Lab, we run our Node.js microservices using PM2 in cluster mode, supervised by systemd, with Nginx as a reverse proxy.
This stack has provided us with 99.9% uptime and seamless deployments.
Let's explore Related Articles.
Docker & Kubernetes Deployment Guide - Containerized Node.js deployments.
GitHub Actions CI/CD Complete Guide - Automate your deployments.
Nginx Reverse Proxy & Load Balancing Guide - Front your Node.js apps with Nginx.
Apache vs Nginx Web Server Comparison - Choose the right reverse proxy.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.