You're listening to: Postgres Index Bloat Nearly Took Down Production: A VACUUM Deep-Dive.
A table that was 2 GB of data carried 14 GB of dead tuples and bloated indexes.
How MVCC creates bloat, how to measure it, and how autovacuum tuning, HOT updates, and a careful REINDEX brought query times back from 3s to 40ms.
Let's get started.
Our lab_results table held about 2 GB of actual data.
On disk, it and its indexes occupied 31 GB.
Queries that used to return in 40ms were creeping past 3 seconds.
Nothing in the schema had changed; the row count had barely grown.
The disk was just... filling up, and the database was getting slower in lockstep.
The culprit was bloat — and understanding it means understanding how PostgreSQL handles updates under the hood.
This is the deep-dive I wish I'd read before the incident.
For the broader scaling picture, pair it with database sharding & partitioning and PostgreSQL performance optimization.
Now, let's talk about Why Postgres creates dead rows: MVCC.
PostgreSQL uses MVCC (Multi-Version Concurrency Control) so that readers never block writers.
The trick: when you UPDATE a row, Postgres does not overwrite it.
It writes a new version of the row and marks the old version as dead (a "dead tuple").
Transactions that started before the update still see the old version; new ones see the new version.
A DELETE similarly just marks the row dead.
This is brilliant for concurrency and terrible if you ignore it, because those dead tuples don't disappear on their own.
Every update to a row leaves a corpse behind.
Our lab_results table got a status update several times per result — each one creating a new live tuple and a dead one.
Multiply by millions of results and you get 14 GB of dead tuples sitting in a 2 GB table.
The mechanism that reclaims this space is VACUUM.
Moving on to Measuring the damage.
Before touching anything, measure.
This query shows dead-tuple counts and the last (auto)vacuum time per table:
Ours showed lab_results with a dead_ratio near 7 — seven dead tuples for every live one — and a last_autovacuum of three weeks ago.
Autovacuum, the background process that is supposed to clean this up, had effectively stopped keeping up.
For index bloat specifically, pgstattuple gives the truth:
Our primary index was at ~22% leaf density — meaning ~78% of the index pages were wasted space.
That is why query times had quadrupled: every index scan was reading four times more pages than it needed to.
Next up: Why autovacuum fell behind.
Autovacuum is triggered per-table when dead tuples exceed a threshold:
The default scale_factor is 0.2 — autovacuum only kicks in after 20% of the table is dead.
On a large, update-heavy table, 20% is a lot of dead tuples, and by the time autovacuum runs it has a huge amount to clean.
Worse, our autovacuum was being throttled by conservative cost-delay settings and was getting cancelled by an ALTER/lock from a nightly job before it finished.
Two configuration changes fixed the ongoing problem.
I tuned them per-table rather than globally, because only a few hot tables needed it:
Vacuuming little and often is far cheaper than vacuuming rarely and enormously.
Let's explore Reducing bloat at the source: HOT updates.
The best bloat is the kind you never create.
PostgreSQL has an optimization called HOT (Heap-Only Tuple) updates: if an update does not change any indexed column, and there's room on the same page, Postgres can update the row in place without touching every index.
HOT updates dramatically reduce both table and index bloat.
We were defeating it.
Our status-update query touched an indexed updated_at column on every write, so no update qualified as HOT.
Two changes helped:
Don't index columns that change on every write unless you truly query by them.
We dropped an index on a high-churn column..
Lower the table's fillfactor so each page leaves room for in-place updates:.
A fillfactor of 85 leaves 15% of each page free for HOT updates to land in place.
After a rewrite, the ratio of HOT updates (n_tup_hot_upd / n_tup_upd in pg_stat_user_tables) jumped from near-zero to over 90%, and bloat accumulation slowed to a crawl.
Now let's look at Reclaiming the space already lost.
Tuning stops new bloat; it does not shrink the 31 GB you already have.
VACUUM marks dead space reusable but rarely returns it to the OS.
To actually reclaim disk, you have two options:
VACUUM FULL — fully rewrites the table compactly, but takes an ACCESS EXCLUSIVE lock (the table is unavailable for the duration).
Fine at 3 AM on a small table; unacceptable on a hot one..
pg_repack — rebuilds the table and indexes with only brief locking, online.
This is what I used..
For the indexes specifically, REINDEX INDEX CONCURRENTLY (Postgres 12+) rebuilds a bloated index without blocking writes:
After repack + concurrent reindex, the table-plus-indexes footprint dropped from 31 GB to 2.4 GB, and the patient-lookup query went from ~3s back to ~40ms.
Now, let's talk about Results.
Metric, Before, After.
On-disk size (table + indexes), 31 GB, 2.4 GB.
Dead-tuple ratio, ~7.0, ~0.1.
Index leaf density, ~22%, ~91%.
Patient-lookup query, ~3,000ms, ~40ms.
HOT update ratio, ~3%, ~92%.
Moving on to The checklist I now run on every write-heavy table.
Monitor n_dead_tup and last_autovacuum in pg_stat_user_tables.
Silent autovacuum failure is the root of most bloat incidents..
Tune autovacuum_vacuum_scale_factor per hot table (0.01–0.05), not globally..
Protect HOT updates: don't index high-churn columns; set a fillfactor around 85 on update-heavy tables..
Reclaim space online with pg_repack and REINDEX ...
CONCURRENTLY, not VACUUM FULL, on anything user-facing..
Watch long-running transactions — they hold back the "oldest visible" horizon and can prevent vacuum from removing dead tuples at all..
Bloat is not a bug in Postgres; it is the cost of MVCC, and MVCC is why Postgres handles concurrency so gracefully.
The job is to keep the cleanup keeping pace.
For where to go when a single node is no longer enough, see database sharding & partitioning.
Related reading: PostgreSQL Performance Optimization.
Database Sharding & Partitioning: An Advanced Guide.
Database Connection Pooling: The Performance Fix That Saved Our Production.
MongoDB vs PostgreSQL: A Database Comparison.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.