You're listening to: Migrating to Post-Quantum Cryptography: A Practical Developer Guide (2026).
Harvest-now-decrypt-later means quantum-vulnerable data is already being stolen today.
A practical, no-hype migration guide: crypto-agility, where ML-KEM and ML-DSA fit, the hybrid rollout, and a concrete inventory-first plan for engineering teams.
Let's get started.
The uncomfortable truth about post-quantum cryptography is that you cannot wait for a quantum computer to exist before you act.
Adversaries are already running a strategy called harvest-now, decrypt-later: capture encrypted traffic today, store it, and decrypt it years from now when a cryptographically-relevant quantum computer arrives.
If your data needs to stay secret for a decade — health records, financial data, state secrets, even long-lived auth tokens — then for that data, the quantum threat is a present-day threat.
This is the practical migration guide I wish existed when I started building QuantumShield and QAuth.
No hype, no "quantum apocalypse" — just what an engineering team should actually do in 2026.
Now, let's talk about What quantum computers break (and what they don't).
Two quantum algorithms matter for cryptography:
Shor's algorithm efficiently factors large integers and solves discrete logarithms.
This breaks RSA, Diffie-Hellman, and elliptic-curve cryptography (ECDH, ECDSA) — the asymmetric primitives that protect virtually all key exchange and digital signatures today..
Grover's algorithm gives a quadratic speed-up on brute-force search.
This weakens symmetric crypto, but only mildly: AES-128 effectively drops to ~64-bit security, while AES-256 remains safe.
SHA-256/SHA-3 are similarly fine at appropriate sizes..
So the headline is precise: symmetric crypto is mostly OK; asymmetric crypto is the problem.
Your TLS key exchange and your signatures are what need replacing — not your AES-256 data encryption.
Moving on to The NIST standards you'll actually use.
In 2024 NIST finalized the first post-quantum standards.
Three matter for most engineers:
Standard, Name, Replaces, Use for.
FIPS 203, ML-KEM (Kyber), ECDH / RSA key exchange, Establishing shared secrets / key encapsulation.
FIPS 204, ML-DSA (Dilithium), ECDSA / RSA signatures, Digital signatures, token signing.
FIPS 205, SLH-DSA (SPHINCS+), —, Conservative, hash-based signatures (firmware, roots of trust).
ML-KEM is a Key Encapsulation Mechanism — it is how two parties agree on a shared secret in a quantum-safe way.
ML-DSA is a signature scheme.
If you understand "ECDH for key exchange, ECDSA for signatures," then the mapping is simply ML-KEM and ML-DSA respectively.
I go deeper on choosing between them in ML-KEM vs ML-DSA.
Next up: The one principle that makes migration survivable: crypto-agility.
The single biggest mistake teams make is hard-coding algorithms.
If RSA is hard-wired across your codebase, swapping it is a months-long, error-prone slog.
The fix is crypto-agility: route every cryptographic operation through an abstraction that names the algorithm as data, not as code.
Crypto-agility is what lets you roll out PQC incrementally, run hybrids, and — critically — roll back if a new scheme is found weak.
PQC schemes are younger than RSA; agility is your insurance policy.
Let's explore Why you deploy hybrids first, not pure PQC.
The recommended migration path is hybrid: combine a battle-tested classical algorithm with a post-quantum one, so the result is secure if either holds.
For key exchange, you derive the session key from both an ECDH secret and an ML-KEM secret.
For signatures, you attach both an Ed25519 and an ML-DSA signature and require both to verify.
The reasoning is risk symmetry:
Classical crypto (RSA/ECC) is proven against classical attacks but doomed against quantum ones..
PQC is quantum-resistant but younger and less battle-tested against classical cryptanalysis..
A hybrid is broken only if both are broken — covering you against a quantum computer and against an unforeseen weakness in the newer PQC scheme..
This is exactly the design choice behind QAuth's dual Ed25519 + ML-DSA-65 signatures.
I unpack the trade-offs in why hybrid Ed25519 + ML-DSA is the safe path.
Pure PQC is the destination; hybrid is how you travel there safely.
Now let's look at A concrete migration plan.
You do not migrate "the company."
You migrate one cryptographic dependency at a time, highest-risk first.
1. Inventory your cryptography.
You cannot protect what you cannot see.
Build a cryptographic bill of materials: every place you use asymmetric crypto — TLS endpoints, JWT/token signing, mTLS between services, code signing, stored encrypted blobs, VPNs, database TLS.
For each, record the algorithm, key size, and — most importantly — how long the protected data must stay confidential.
2. Prioritize by data lifetime.
Apply the harvest-now-decrypt-later lens.
Sort by (confidentiality_lifetime × exposure
Urgent: long-lived secrets crossing networks that adversaries can capture — health records, financial data, anything regulated for 7–10+ years..
Later: ephemeral data whose value evaporates in minutes (a short-lived session that's worthless once expired)..
Data that must stay secret until 2040 needs quantum-safe key exchange today, even though no quantum computer exists yet.
3. Add crypto-agility where it's missing.
Before swapping algorithms, introduce the abstraction layer.
This is often the largest engineering task and the most valuable one.
4. Roll out hybrids, behind flags.
Deploy hybrid key exchange and hybrid signatures behind feature flags, starting with internal service-to-service traffic where you control both ends.
Measure the overhead (ML-KEM/ML-DSA keys and signatures are larger than ECC — expect bigger handshakes and tokens) and watch your tail latencies.
5. Monitor, then expand.
Verify interoperability, watch error rates and latency, then widen the rollout outward to external-facing endpoints as client support matures.
Now, let's talk about What this costs you.
Be honest with stakeholders about the trade-offs:
Larger keys and signatures.
ML-DSA-65 signatures are several kilobytes versus ~64 bytes for Ed25519.
This inflates tokens, certificates, and handshake sizes — relevant for bandwidth-constrained or high-QPS systems..
More CPU, though modern lattice implementations are fast — often competitive with or faster than RSA for equivalent operations..
Maturing tooling.
Library, HSM, and browser support is improving rapidly but is not yet universal.
Hybrid mode is partly what bridges that gap..
None of these are blockers.
They are planning inputs.
Moving on to The takeaway.
Post-quantum migration is not a fire drill, but it is also not optional, and the "harvest now" reality means the clock for long-lived data has already started.
The winning strategy is unglamorous: inventory your crypto, make it agile, and roll out hybrids worst-case-first.
Teams that build crypto-agility now will swap algorithms in an afternoon; teams that hard-coded RSA will spend quarters on it.
Start with the abstraction layer — everything else follows from it.
Related reading: QAuth: The Post-Quantum Authentication Protocol That Replaces OAuth 2.0 and JWT.
QuantumShield: Building a Post-Quantum Cryptography Library from Scratch.
ML-KEM vs ML-DSA: NIST's Post-Quantum Standards Explained.
Hybrid Cryptography: Why Ed25519 + ML-DSA Is the Safe Migration Path.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.