You're listening to: PostgreSQL Performance Optimization: Complete Guide for Production.
Master PostgreSQL performance tuning with indexing strategies, query optimization, configuration tuning, and monitoring.
Learn techniques that helped us handle 10M+ daily transactions in healthcare systems.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
PostgreSQL is the database of choice for many production systems, but poor configuration and unoptimized queries can cripple performance.
At Dr. Dangs Lab, we process over 10 million healthcare transactions daily with PostgreSQL.
Here's everything I've learned about making it fast.
Moving on to Understanding PostgreSQL Performance.
The Query Execution Pipeline.
Key Performance Metrics.
Next up: Indexing Strategies.
B-Tree Indexes (Default).
Specialized Index Types.
Index Analysis.
Let's explore Query Optimization.
Using EXPLAIN ANALYZE.
Common Query Optimizations.
CTEs vs Subqueries.
Now let's look at Configuration Tuning.
Memory Settings.
Connection Pooling with PgBouncer.
Application-Side Connection Management.
Now, let's talk about Partitioning for Large Tables.
Moving on to Maintenance and Monitoring.
Automated Maintenance.
Monitoring Queries.
Next up: Key Takeaways.
Index strategically - Not all columns need indexes, but missing indexes kill performance.
Use EXPLAIN ANALYZE - Always understand what your queries are doing.
Configure memory properly - shared_buffers and work_mem have huge impact.
Use connection pooling - PgBouncer is essential for high-concurrency apps.
Partition large tables - Time-series data benefits greatly from partitioning.
Monitor constantly - pg_stat_statements and slow query logs are your friends.
Maintain regularly - VACUUM and ANALYZE keep the database healthy.
Let's explore Conclusion.
PostgreSQL performance optimization is a continuous process.
Start with proper indexing and query optimization, then tune configuration, and finally implement advanced features like partitioning as your data grows.
The key is to measure, optimize, and measure again.
Need help optimizing your PostgreSQL database?
Connect on LinkedIn.
Now let's look at Related Articles.
MongoDB vs PostgreSQL: Database Comparison - Choose the right database.
Redis Caching Strategies Complete Guide - Cache for faster queries.
System Design Interview Guide - Design scalable data systems.
AWS Services for Backend Developers - Managed RDS on AWS.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.