You're listening to: Post-Quantum Cryptography Deadlines: What 2027, 2030 & 2035 Mean for Your Stack.
NSA's CNSA 2.0 sets a 2027 acquisition deadline; NIST deprecates RSA-2048 and ECC P-256 by 2030 and disallows them by 2035.
A plain-English guide to the PQC timeline and what each date actually requires you to do.
Let's get started.
For years, "quantum threat" was a vague future problem.
In 2026 it has dates on it.
NIST's post-quantum standards are final, the NSA has published hard deadlines, and analysts are calling the enterprise transition a $15 billion migration.
If you build or run systems that use cryptography — which is to say, all of them — the timeline has moved from "someday" to a calendar you can plan against.
This is the plain-English version: what 2027, 2030, and 2035 actually mean, and what each date requires you to do.
For the engineering how-to, pair it with my practical PQC migration guide.
Now, let's talk about The two reasons the clock is already ticking.
Before the dates, the two facts that make them urgent:
Harvest-now, decrypt-later.
Adversaries can capture encrypted traffic today and decrypt it once a quantum computer arrives.
So for any data that must stay secret for 5–10+ years, the deadline isn't when quantum computers exist — it's now..
Migrations take 5–15 years.
NIST's own guidance describes the realistic horizon for a full cryptographic transition as five to fifteen years.
The "2035" date is not far away when the work takes that long..
Together these mean the comfortable-sounding deadlines are actually tight.
Moving on to The timeline.
Date, Who sets it, What it means.
Aug 2024, NIST, FIPS 203 (ML-KEM), 204 (ML-DSA), 205 (SLH-DSA) finalized — the standards exist.
Jan 1, 2027, NSA (CNSA 2.0), New US National Security System acquisitions must support PQC.
2030, NIST (IR 8547), RSA-2048 and ECC P-256 deprecated (discouraged, allowed with risk).
2033–2035, NSA / NIST, CNSA 2.0 exclusive for many classes; quantum-vulnerable algorithms disallowed in NIST standards by 2035.
What "2027" requires.
The NSA's CNSA 2.0 suite becomes mandatory for new national-security-system acquisitions from January 1, 2027.
Even if you're not a government contractor, this date matters: it sets the tone for the whole supply chain.
Vendors selling to government must ship PQC, which means the libraries, HSMs, and products you depend on will have quantum-safe options by then — and procurement teams will start asking for them.
If you sell software, "do you support PQC?" becomes a real question on security questionnaires around this date.
What "2030" requires (deprecated).
In NIST's vocabulary, deprecated means an algorithm is still allowed but discouraged, and its use carries acknowledged risk.
By 2030, RSA-2048 and ECC P-256 — the asymmetric workhorses behind most TLS and signatures today — hit this status.
Practically: by 2030 you should have PQC (in hybrid mode) deployed for anything long-lived, and a concrete plan to retire pure-classical asymmetric crypto.
Auditors and frameworks will start flagging deprecated algorithms.
What "2035" requires (disallowed).
Disallowed is the hard stop: the algorithm may no longer be used in compliant systems.
By 2035, quantum-vulnerable algorithms are removed from NIST standards entirely.
If you're still running RSA/ECC for key exchange or signatures in a regulated context at that point, you're out of compliance.
2035 sounds distant, but at a 5–15 year migration horizon, a program that starts in 2026 is on schedule, not early.
Next up: What this means for you, by situation.
You build SaaS / web services.
Plan hybrid TLS (X25519 + ML-KEM) and PQC-capable signing on the 2030 horizon.
Start your crypto inventory now (below).
Long-lived secrets are the urgent part..
You sell software to enterprises/government.
"PQC support" becomes a sales requirement around 2027.
Being early is a differentiator on security questionnaires..
You handle long-confidentiality data (health, finance, legal, government — exactly the kind I've built for).
Harvest-now-decrypt-later makes this your most urgent category regardless of the headline dates..
You're an individual engineer.
PQC fluency is becoming a hiring signal.
Understanding ML-KEM vs ML-DSA and hybrid cryptography is a genuinely scarce, valuable skill..
Let's explore The first concrete step (do this in 2026).
You cannot migrate what you cannot see.
The universal starting move — the one every framework and the NCSC and NIST all agree on — is to build a cryptographic inventory, a Cryptographic Bill of Materials (CBOM): every place you use asymmetric crypto, the algorithm, and how long the data it protects must stay confidential.
That inventory, sorted by data lifetime, is your migration plan.
I walk through building one in Cryptographic Bill of Materials (CBOM): Step 1 of PQC Migration.
The second move is crypto-agility — routing crypto through an abstraction so swapping algorithms is config, not a rewrite.
That's what turns these deadlines from a panic into a schedule, and it's the core of the migration guide.
Now let's look at The takeaway.
The post-quantum transition now has real dates: 2027 (NSA acquisitions), 2030 (RSA/ECC deprecated), 2035 (disallowed).
Because migrations take 5–15 years and "harvest now, decrypt later" is already in play, a program that begins in 2026 with a crypto inventory and an agility layer is exactly on time.
The organizations that treat these as a 2034 problem will be the ones doing it in a panic; the ones that start their CBOM this year will swap algorithms calmly when the deadlines land.
Related reading: Migrating to Post-Quantum Cryptography: A Practical Developer Guide (2026).
Cryptographic Bill of Materials (CBOM): Step 1 of PQC Migration.
ML-KEM vs ML-DSA: NIST's Post-Quantum Standards Explained.
QAuth: The Post-Quantum Authentication Protocol.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.