You're listening to: PSQA Implementation Roadmap: Technical Milestones and First Steps.
A detailed technical roadmap for implementing the Phonon-mediated Silicon Carbide Quantum Architecture, from first experiments to million-qubit systems.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about PSQA Implementation Roadmap.
Moving on to From First Experiment to Million Qubits.
This document provides a detailed technical roadmap for implementing PSQA (Phonon-mediated Silicon Carbide Quantum Architecture).
Unlike high-level business plans, this focuses on the actual experiments, equipment, and milestones needed to build a room-temperature quantum computer.
Next up: Phase 1: Foundation Experiments (Months 1-18).
1.1 Initial Lab Setup.
1.2 First Experiments: Single V_Si Characterization.
1.3 Spin Readout Experiments.
1.4 Coherent Spin Control.
Let's explore Phase 2: Phononic Coupling (Months 18-36).
2.1 Phononic Crystal Fabrication.
2.2 Phonon-Spin Coupling Measurement.
2.3 Two-Qubit Gate via Phonon Exchange.
Now let's look at Phase 3: Scaling and Error Correction (Months 36-72).
3.1 Multi-Qubit Arrays.
3.2 Error Correction Implementation.
Now, let's talk about Phase 4: Million-Qubit System (Months 72-120).
4.1 Multi-Chip Optical Interconnect.
4.2 Final System Integration.
Moving on to Risk Mitigation.
Next up: Conclusion.
This roadmap provides a concrete path from first experiments to a million-qubit quantum computer.
The key milestones are:
Month 18: Single V_Si qubit control (validates basic physics).
Month 36: Two-qubit phonon-mediated gate (validates architecture).
Month 60: 100-qubit chip with error correction (validates scaling).
Month 120: Million-qubit system (validates practical QC).
Each phase builds on the previous, with clear go/no-go criteria.
The total investment required is approximately $100M over 10 years - a fraction of what competitors are spending on less scalable approaches.
The path is challenging but achievable.
Let's build it.
Document Version: 1.0 Date: February 2026 Author: Tushar Agrawal
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.