You're listening to: Python Async Programming with asyncio: Complete Developer Guide.
Master asynchronous programming in Python with asyncio.
Learn coroutines, tasks, event loops, async context managers, and build high-performance concurrent applications with practical examples.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
Asynchronous programming is essential for building high-performance Python applications.
At Dr. Dangs Lab, we use asyncio to handle thousands of concurrent API requests, database queries, and external service calls.
This guide covers everything you need to master async Python.
Moving on to Understanding Async/Await.
Synchronous vs Asynchronous.
How asyncio Works.
Next up: Coroutines, Tasks, and Futures.
Coroutines.
Tasks - Concurrent Execution.
Task Management.
Let's explore Async Context Managers and Iterators.
Async Context Managers.
Using contextlib for async context managers.
Async Iterators.
Async Generators.
Now let's look at Real-World Patterns.
HTTP Client with aiohttp.
Database Operations with asyncpg.
Producer-Consumer Pattern.
Async Retry Pattern.
Now, let's talk about Error Handling.
Handling Multiple Task Errors.
Graceful Shutdown.
Moving on to Performance Tips.
Avoid Blocking Calls.
Batching with asyncio.gather.
Next up: Key Takeaways.
Use async for I/O-bound operations - Network, database, file operations.
Never block the event loop - Use run_in_executor for CPU-bound work.
Create tasks for concurrency - asyncio.gather and create_task.
Implement proper cleanup - Use async context managers.
Handle timeouts - Use asyncio.wait_for.
Limit concurrency - Use Semaphore to prevent resource exhaustion.
Stream large data - Use async generators.
Let's explore Conclusion.
Async programming in Python unlocks massive performance improvements for I/O-bound applications.
Start with simple coroutines, learn to use tasks for concurrency, and gradually adopt advanced patterns like producer-consumer queues.
The investment in learning async pays dividends in application performance.
Building async Python applications?
Connect on LinkedIn to discuss best practices.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.