You're listening to: QAuth: The Post-Quantum Authentication Protocol That Replaces OAuth 2.0 and JWT.
Deep dive into QuantumAuth (QAuth), a next-generation authentication protocol with dual signatures (Ed25519 + ML-DSA-65), encrypted payloads, mandatory proof-of-possession, and built-in revocation.
Why OAuth 2.0 and JWT are fundamentally broken and how QAuth fixes everything.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about The Problem: OAuth 2.0 and JWT Are Fundamentally Broken.
Every security researcher knows it.
Every production breach proves it.
OAuth 2.0 and JWT have critical, unfixable vulnerabilities that have led to billions of compromised accounts.
Let me be direct about what's wrong.
OAuth 2.0: Death by a Thousand Cuts.
JWT: The Algorithm Confusion Nightmare.
JWT's design is fundamentally flawed.
The header contains the algorithm, meaning the attacker chooses how to verify:
Real-world impact: These aren't theoretical - they've caused breaches at major companies.
The Auth0 vulnerability (CVE-2022-23529), the PyJWT issues, countless custom implementations getting it wrong.
What's Missing From Current Standards.
Feature, OAuth 2.0, JWT, Required.
Post-quantum crypto, No, No, Yes.
Encrypted payloads, No, No, Yes.
Proof of possession, Optional (DPoP), No, Mandatory.
Built-in revocation, No, No, Yes.
Safe algorithm selection, No, No, Yes.
Device binding, No, No, Yes.
Fine-grained authorization, Scope explosion, Limited, Policy-based.
Moving on to Introducing QAuth: Authentication Rebuilt from First Principles.
QAuth is a complete replacement for OAuth 2.0 and JWT, designed with one goal: secure by default, not by configuration.
Next up: QToken Format: The Anti-JWT.
Unlike JWT's vulnerable header.payload.signature format with attacker-controlled algorithms, QToken uses a fixed, binary format:
Why This Format Matters.
No algorithm field - Server enforces Ed25519 + ML-DSA-65, period.
Encrypted claims - Payloads are private, preventing information leakage.
Dual signatures - Both classical and post-quantum must verify.
Proof binding - Token bound to specific device and client keys.
Let's explore Dual Signature System: Belt and Suspenders.
QAuth uses dual signatures for defense-in-depth:
Why dual signatures?
If Ed25519 is broken by quantum computers, ML-DSA-65 remains secure.
If ML-DSA-65 has an undiscovered flaw, Ed25519 is battle-tested.
Both must verify - attacker must break both simultaneously.
Now let's look at Mandatory Proof of Possession.
Unlike OAuth's bearer tokens that work from any device, QAuth requires every request to prove key possession:
Implementation Example.
Now, let's talk about Built-in Revocation System.
JWT's stateless nature means tokens can't be revoked without external systems.
QAuth solves this with built-in revocation:
Revocation Implementation.
Moving on to Policy-Based Authorization (No Scope Explosion).
OAuth's scope system doesn't scale.
QAuth uses policy references instead:
Benefits of Policy References.
Token stays small - Just a reference, not all permissions.
Policies update without re-issuing tokens - Change server-side.
Supports RBAC, ABAC, ReBAC - One unified system.
Context-aware conditions - Time, location, device, MFA status.
Audit-friendly - Clear policy documents.
Next up: Complete QAuth Flow.
Let's explore Security Analysis: QAuth vs Known Attacks.
JWT Attacks - All Mitigated.
Attack, JWT Vulnerable, QAuth Protected, How.
Algorithm confusion, Yes, N/A, No algorithm field.
"None" algorithm, Yes, N/A, Algorithm not configurable.
Key ID injection, Yes, No, KeyID is hash of public key.
Signature bypass, Yes, No, Server enforces verification.
Token replay, Yes, No, Proof of possession.
Token theft, Yes, No, Bound to device/client key.
Payload inspection, Yes, No, Encrypted, not encoded.
Expiry extension, Yes, No, Encrypted expiry.
OAuth 2.0 Attacks - All Mitigated.
Attack, OAuth Vulnerable, QAuth Protected, How.
Redirect URI manipulation, Yes, No, Cryptographic binding.
Authorization code interception, Yes, No, Bound to client public key.
PKCE downgrade, Yes, N/A, PKCE mandatory.
Bearer token theft, Yes, No, Proof of possession required.
Cross-app attacks, Yes, No, Client key binding.
Token reuse, Yes, No, Request-specific proofs.
Post-Quantum Security.
Threat, Current Status, QAuth Protection.
Harvest-now-decrypt-later, Active threat, ML-DSA-65 signatures.
Quantum signature forgery, Future threat, Dual Ed25519 + ML-DSA-65.
Quantum key compromise, Future threat, Keys derived with SHA3-512.
Now let's look at SDK Availability.
QAuth is available in multiple languages:
Rust (Reference Implementation).
TypeScript/JavaScript.
Python.
Go.
Now, let's talk about Performance Benchmarks.
QAuth performance on modern hardware:
Moving on to Migration Path from OAuth 2.0.
Phase 1: QAuth Gateway.
Deploy QAuth as a proxy in front of existing OAuth:
Phase 2: Hybrid Mode.
Auth server issues both OAuth and QAuth tokens:
Phase 3: Native QAuth.
Full QAuth implementation, OAuth deprecated:
Next up: Why Use QAuth?.
For Security Teams.
Eliminates entire attack classes - No algorithm confusion, no bearer token theft.
Post-quantum ready - Dual signatures protect against future quantum attacks.
Built-in revocation - 5-minute worst-case revocation window.
Audit-friendly - Clear policy documents, encrypted-by-default.
For Developers.
Simpler mental model - No complex security configurations.
Type-safe SDKs - Rust, TypeScript, Python, Go.
Policy updates without re-deployment - Change server-side policies.
Better error messages - Clear validation failures.
For Compliance.
NIST FIPS 204 compliant - ML-DSA-65 signatures.
Encrypted at rest and in transit - Payloads never exposed.
Fine-grained access control - RBAC, ABAC, ReBAC supported.
Complete audit trail - Every access logged with proof.
Let's explore Getting Started.
Installation.
Quick Start.
Now let's look at Conclusion.
OAuth 2.0 and JWT served their purpose, but their fundamental design flaws can't be fixed with patches.
QAuth is built from first principles:
Secure by default - No configuration required for security.
Post-quantum ready - Dual signatures protect against future threats.
Proof of possession - Stolen tokens are useless.
Built-in revocation - Instant invalidation.
Encrypted payloads - Privacy by design.
Policy-based authorization - No scope explosion.
The quantum computing threat isn't hypothetical.
Nation-states are harvesting encrypted data today.
QAuth ensures your authentication system will remain secure when quantum computers arrive.
Now, let's talk about Resources.
QAuth Specification.
Rust Implementation.
TypeScript SDK - npm install @quantumshield/qauth.
Python SDK - pip install qauth.
Go SDK.
QuantumShield Crypto Library.
QAuth is part of the QuantumShield project, bringing post-quantum cryptography to authentication.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.