You're listening to: Quantum Computing Part 3: Hands-On Tutorials, Interview Prep & Startup Landscape (2026).
Part 3: Build your first quantum circuit step-by-step.
Qiskit vs Cirq vs Q# comparison.
Interview preparation guide.
Quantum startup funding ($3.77B in 2025).
Common myths debunked.
Error correction explained simply.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Welcome to Part 3.
In Part 1, we covered basics and breakthroughs.
In Part 2, we covered applications and careers.
Part 3 gets hands-on: Build your first quantum circuit (step-by-step code).
Qiskit vs Cirq vs Q# - which to learn?.
Quantum error correction explained simply.
Interview preparation guide.
Startup funding landscape ($3.77B in 2025).
Common myths debunked by experts.
Let's build something.
Moving on to Part 1: Build Your First Quantum Circuit.
Stop reading theory.
Let's write actual code.
Setup (5 Minutes).
Project 1: Quantum Coin Flip (Beginner).
The simplest quantum program - true randomness from quantum mechanics.
What Just Happened:
Project 2: Bell State / Entanglement (Intermediate).
Create two entangled qubits - Einstein's "spooky action."
Why This Is Mind-Blowing:
Project 3: Grover's Search (Advanced).
Find a needle in a haystack - quantumly.
The Power of Grover's:
Run on REAL Quantum Hardware.
Next up: Part 2: Qiskit vs Cirq vs Q# - Which to Learn?.
Three major frameworks.
Here's the honest comparison.
Quick Comparison Table.
Detailed Breakdown.
My Recommendation.
Let's explore Part 3: Quantum Error Correction Made Simple.
The #1 challenge in quantum computing, explained without PhD jargon.
The Problem.
The Solution: Redundancy.
Surface Codes Explained Simply.
The 2025 Breakthrough: Below Threshold.
What This Means for You.
Now let's look at Part 4: Interview Preparation Guide.
Land that $200K+ quantum job.
Market Reality.
What Interviewers Ask.
Algorithm Questions.
Preparation Timeline.
What Companies Want.
Now, let's talk about Part 5: Startup Funding & Investment Landscape.
$3.77 billion flowed into quantum in 9 months of 2025.
2025 Funding Explosion.
Major Funding Rounds (2025).
Public Companies & Valuations.
Startup Categories.
India's Quantum Startups.
Moving on to Part 6: Quantum Myths Debunked.
Experts from IBM, Google, and NVIDIA weigh in.
Myth 1: Quantum Will Replace Classical Computers.
Myth 2: Quantum Computers Are Always Faster.
Myth 3: Quantum Computers Use Parallel Universes.
Myth 4: Quantum Will Break All Encryption Immediately.
Myth 5: "Always 10 Years Away".
Myth 6: You Need a Physics PhD.
Next up: Part 7: Quantum Advantage vs Supremacy.
The terminology debate, clarified.
Definitions.
Why Terminology Matters.
Current State.
Let's explore Summary: Part 3 Key Takeaways.
Now let's look at What's Next?.
You've completed the quantum computing trilogy: Part 1: Fundamentals & Breakthroughs.
Part 2: Applications & Careers.
Part 3: Hands-On & Advanced Topics.
Your Next Steps: Create IBM Quantum account (free).
Run the code examples in this guide.
Complete Qiskit basics course.
Build a portfolio project.
Join quantum communities.
The quantum era is here.
Now you're ready for it.
Now, let's talk about Related Articles.
Part 1: Quantum Computing Complete Beginner's Guide.
Part 2: Applications, Careers & How to Start.
AI Capabilities in 2026: Complete Guide.
Moving on to Sources and References.
Tutorials & Frameworks: IBM Quantum Documentation.
Qiskit Medium Projects.
Quantum Zeitgeist - Framework Comparison.
Error Correction: Nature - Below Threshold Achievement.
QuEra - Surface Codes Explained.
Azure Quantum - Error Correction.
Interview Preparation: InterviewBee - 2025 Guide.
Quantum Jobs List - Interview Prep.
Patent PC - Job Market Analysis.
Funding & Startups: SpinQ - 2025 Funding Analysis.
Crunchbase - Venture Highmark.
The Quantum Insider - Public Companies.
Myths Debunked: The Quantum Insider - Myth Busters Study.
Quantropi - Common Myths.
FROMDEV - 6 Myths Debunked.
Part 3 of our quantum computing trilogy.
All code tested.
All facts verified.
Last updated: January 27, 2026.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.