You're listening to: Rate Limiting & API Gateway Patterns: Production Implementation Guide.
Master API rate limiting with token bucket, sliding window, and distributed algorithms.
Implement Kong, Nginx, and custom rate limiters with Redis for high-traffic production systems.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
When your API goes viral or faces a DDoS attack, rate limiting is your first line of defense.
It protects backend services from overload, ensures fair usage, and maintains system stability under pressure.
Having built rate limiting systems for healthcare APIs handling millions of requests, I've learned that the algorithm choice and implementation details matter enormously.
This guide covers everything from basic concepts to distributed rate limiting at scale.
Moving on to Rate Limiting Algorithms.
1. Token Bucket Algorithm.
The token bucket is the most versatile algorithm, allowing bursts while maintaining average rate limits.
2. Sliding Window Algorithm.
More accurate than fixed windows, prevents the "boundary problem."
3. Leaky Bucket Algorithm.
Smooths out bursty traffic for consistent throughput.
Next up: FastAPI Rate Limiting Middleware.
Let's explore API Gateway Configuration.
Kong Rate Limiting.
Nginx Rate Limiting.
Now let's look at Distributed Rate Limiting Patterns.
Cluster-Wide Rate Limiting.
Circuit Breaker with Rate Limiting.
Now, let's talk about Monitoring Rate Limits.
Moving on to Conclusion.
Effective rate limiting protects your APIs from abuse while ensuring fair resource allocation:
Token Bucket for APIs needing burst tolerance.
Sliding Window for accurate counting without boundary issues.
Leaky Bucket for traffic shaping and smoothing.
Distributed implementations with Redis for multi-instance deployments.
Tiered limits for different customer segments.
Remember to: Always return proper 429 responses with Retry-After headers.
Monitor rate limit metrics to tune thresholds.
Implement graceful degradation with circuit breakers.
Use consistent hashing for distributed rate limiting.
Next up: Related Articles.
Nginx Reverse Proxy Load Balancing Guide - Traffic management.
Redis Caching Strategies - Redis patterns.
Building Scalable Microservices - Service architecture.
REST API Design Best Practices - API design.
System Design Interview Guide - Architecture patterns.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.