You're listening to: Critical Security Vulnerabilities in React Server Components: What You Need to Know.
Understanding the recent CVE-2025-55182, CVE-2025-55183, CVE-2025-55184, and CVE-2025-67779 vulnerabilities in React Server Components.
Learn about Denial of Service, Source Code Exposure risks, and how to protect your applications.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
The React team has disclosed critical security vulnerabilities affecting React Server Components that require immediate attention.
As someone building production applications with React at Dr. Dangs Lab, I want to break down these vulnerabilities and explain what you need to do to protect your applications.
Moving on to The Vulnerabilities Overview.
In December 2024, security researchers discovered multiple severe vulnerabilities in React Server Components:
CVE, Severity, Type, CVSS Score.
CVE-2025-55182, Critical, Remote Code Execution, 9.8.
CVE-2025-55184, High, Denial of Service, 7.5.
CVE-2025-67779, High, Denial of Service, 7.5.
CVE-2025-55183, Medium, Source Code Exposure, 5.3.
Next up: Affected Packages and Versions.
The following packages are affected:
Fixed versions: 19.0.3, 19.1.4, and 19.2.3
Let's explore Understanding the Vulnerabilities.
1. Remote Code Execution (CVE-2025-55182) - Critical.
The most severe vulnerability allows attackers to execute arbitrary code on your server.
This is a classic "React2Shell" scenario where malicious payloads can be crafted to exploit the server-side rendering process.
2. Denial of Service (CVE-2025-55184 & CVE-2025-67779) - High.
Security researchers discovered that specially crafted HTTP requests can cause infinite loops when deserialized by React, effectively hanging the server process.
This vulnerability exists even if your application doesn't explicitly implement React Server Function endpoints—if it supports React Server Components, it may be vulnerable.
3. Source Code Exposure (CVE-2025-55183) - Medium.
A malicious HTTP request sent to a vulnerable Server Function may unsafely return the source code of Server Functions, potentially exposing hardcoded secrets.
What gets exposed:
Now let's look at Immediate Actions Required.
Step 1: Check Your Dependencies.
Step 2: Update to Fixed Versions.
Step 3: Update Your Framework.
If you're using a framework, update it as well:
Now, let's talk about Security Best Practices.
1. Never Hardcode Secrets.
2. Input Validation.
3. Rate Limiting.
4. Monitoring and Alerting.
Moving on to Framework-Specific Guidance.
Next.js.
React Router.
Next up: Is My Application Affected?.
Your application is NOT affected if:
Your React code does not use a server.
You don't use a framework/bundler supporting React Server Components.
You're using React Native without a monorepo or react-dom.
Your application IS affected if:
You use Next.js 13+ with App Router.
You use React Router with Server Components.
You use any of the affected packages.
Let's explore Timeline of Events.
Date, Event.
Dec 3, Leak vulnerability reported.
Dec 4, Initial DoS reported.
Dec 6, Issues confirmed by React team.
Dec 7, Initial fixes created.
Dec 8, Affected parties notified.
Dec 10, Hosting provider mitigations in place.
Dec 11, Patches published, CVEs disclosed.
Now let's look at Key Takeaways.
Update immediately - Don't wait, these are critical vulnerabilities.
Never hardcode secrets - Use environment variables.
Validate all inputs - Server Functions are attack vectors.
Monitor your applications - Set up logging and alerting.
Keep dependencies updated - This pattern of follow-up CVEs is common.
Now, let's talk about Conclusion.
Security vulnerabilities in critical infrastructure like React affect millions of applications.
The React team's quick response and transparent disclosure is commendable.
As developers, we must stay vigilant, keep our dependencies updated, and follow security best practices.
The discovery of follow-up vulnerabilities after the initial patch is a healthy sign of the security community working together.
Always verify your applications are running the latest patched versions.
Have questions about securing your React applications?
Connect on LinkedIn to discuss security best practices.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.