You're listening to: REST API Design Best Practices: Building APIs That Developers Love.
Learn how to design clean, scalable, and developer-friendly REST APIs.
Covers URL structure, HTTP methods, status codes, pagination, versioning, error handling, and security best practices.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
A well-designed API is a joy to work with.
A poorly designed one causes frustration, bugs, and wasted developer hours.
Having built APIs consumed by mobile apps, third-party integrations, and internal services at Dr. Dangs Lab, I've learned what separates great APIs from mediocre ones.
Moving on to RESTful URL Design.
Resource Naming Conventions.
URL Structure Patterns.
Next up: HTTP Methods and Status Codes.
HTTP Methods.
Status Codes Cheat Sheet.
Let's explore Request and Response Design.
Consistent Response Format.
Error Response Format.
Now let's look at Pagination.
Cursor-Based Pagination (Recommended).
Offset-Based Pagination (Simple).
Now, let's talk about Filtering, Sorting, and Field Selection.
Moving on to API Versioning.
Next up: Authentication and Security.
Let's explore Documentation with OpenAPI.
Now let's look at Key Takeaways.
Use nouns, not verbs in URLs - let HTTP methods convey the action.
Be consistent with naming, casing, and response formats.
Use proper status codes - they communicate intent clearly.
Implement pagination - never return unbounded lists.
Version your API - breaking changes will happen.
Document thoroughly - OpenAPI/Swagger is your friend.
Handle errors gracefully - descriptive errors help debugging.
Secure by default - authentication, rate limiting, input validation.
Now, let's talk about Conclusion.
Great API design is about empathy for the developers who will use it.
Follow conventions, be consistent, document well, and handle edge cases gracefully.
Your future self (and your API consumers) will thank you.
Building APIs?
Let's discuss best practices on LinkedIn.
Moving on to Related Articles.
Authentication & Authorization: JWT, OAuth 2.0 Guide - Secure your APIs with proper authentication.
GraphQL vs REST: Which to Choose?
- Compare API paradigms.
Testing Strategies: Unit, Integration, E2E - Test your APIs effectively.
TypeScript Best Practices - Type-safe API development.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.