You're listening to: Top 15 System Design Interview Questions for Indian Tech Companies (2026).
Prepare for system design interviews at Flipkart, Razorpay, Google, Amazon, and Indian startups.
Complete guide with solutions for URL shortener, payment systems, chat apps, and more.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about System Design Interviews in India (2026).
System design interviews are now mandatory at most product companies in India.
Whether you're interviewing at Flipkart, Razorpay, Google, or a well-funded startup, you'll face at least one system design round.
Moving on to How to Approach System Design Questions.
The RESHADED Framework.
Next up: Top 15 System Design Questions.
1. Design a URL Shortener (like Bit.ly).
2. Design WhatsApp/Messaging System.
3. Design Razorpay/Payment System.
4. Design Swiggy/Food Delivery System.
5. Design BookMyShow/Ticket Booking.
6. Design Twitter/Social Feed.
7. Design Uber/Ride Sharing.
8. Design YouTube/Video Streaming.
9. Design Flipkart/E-commerce.
10. Design Google Search.
Let's explore Common Follow-up Questions.
Now let's look at Preparation Strategy.
Now, let's talk about Conclusion.
System design interviews test your ability to think at scale and make trade-offs.
Practice the framework, understand the patterns, and you'll be well-prepared for any system design question.
Preparing for system design interviews?
Let's discuss on LinkedIn.
Moving on to Related Articles.
Backend Developer Roadmap 2026.
Python vs Go for Backend.
Database Connection Pooling.
Microservices Architecture.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.