You're listening to: TypeScript Best Practices: Write Type-Safe, Maintainable Code.
Master TypeScript with advanced patterns, type utilities, generics, strict mode, error handling, and best practices for building scalable applications.
From basics to advanced type manipulation.
Let's get started.
Now, let's talk about Introduction.
TypeScript transforms JavaScript development by adding static types, catching errors at compile time rather than runtime.
This guide covers best practices from basic typing to advanced patterns used in production codebases.
Moving on to Essential Configuration.
Strict tsconfig.json.
Next up: Type Fundamentals.
Prefer Interfaces for Objects.
Const Assertions.
Discriminated Unions.
Let's explore Advanced Type Patterns.
Generic Constraints.
Mapped Types.
Conditional Types.
Template Literal Types.
Now let's look at Error Handling.
Type-Safe Error Classes.
Result Pattern (No Exceptions).
Now, let's talk about API Type Safety.
Request/Response Types.
Zod for Runtime Validation.
Moving on to Utility Patterns.
Builder Pattern.
Factory Pattern.
Next up: Common Anti-Patterns to Avoid.
1. Avoid any.
2. Avoid Type Assertions.
3. Avoid Optional Chaining Abuse.
Let's explore Best Practices Summary.
Enable strict mode - All strict options in tsconfig.json.
Prefer interfaces - For object types that may be extended.
Use const assertions - For literal types and immutability.
Discriminated unions - For handling multiple related types.
Avoid any - Use unknown with type guards instead.
Runtime validation - Use Zod for external data.
Result types - For explicit error handling.
Generic constraints - Make functions type-safe and reusable.
Building type-safe applications?
Connect on LinkedIn to discuss TypeScript patterns and best practices.
Now let's look at Related Articles.
REST API Design Best Practices - Type-safe API design.
Testing Strategies: Unit, Integration, E2E - Test TypeScript code.
Authentication & Authorization Guide - Type-safe auth.
Python Asyncio Complete Guide - Compare with async TypeScript.
And that's the end of this article.
Thanks for listening.